<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[From Shakespeare to Java]]></title>
  <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-10-24T21:32:26-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lori Becker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simplifying Dynamic UIs With React Router]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2019/10/23/simplifying-dynamic-uis-with-react-router/"/>
    <updated>2019-10-23T20:08:46-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2019/10/23/simplifying-dynamic-uis-with-react-router</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Imagine building a React application where the displayed content depends upon some data coming back from an API call. When one of the navigation tabs is clicked at the top of the page, a very specific Component is rendered as the page&rsquo;s content. This seems like an easy problem to solve, right?</p>

<p>For the sake of this example, let&rsquo;s say our React app is to display content about buildings. There are many different types of buildings - homes, shops, skyscrapers, monuments, museums, etc. - obviously, the content for each of them is going to be different. If the API response returns back a property like <code>buildingType</code>, we could probably create a switch statement to return the correct component dynamically:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">getComponent(buildingType) {
  switch(buildingType) {
    case "museum": return Museum;
    case "skyscraper": return Skyscraper;
    ...
    default: return DefaultBuilding;
  }
}

render() {
  const BuildingComponent = this.getComponent(this.state.buildingType);
  return &lt;BuildingComponent /&gt;;
}
</code></pre>

<p>This solution is okay if we&rsquo;re creating a really simple React application. But for an more complicated UI, this isn&rsquo;t going to cut it. Maybe we need to set props on <code>Museum</code> and a totally different set of props on <code>Skyscraper</code>. Now what? Maybe you could convert each case into an object like so:
&#8220;`javascript
case &ldquo;museum&rdquo;: return {
  comp: Museum,
  props: {
    this.state.building.museumType,
    this.state.building.museumRanking
  }
}</p>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<p>render() {
  const building = this.getComponent(this.state.buildingType);
  const BuildingComponent = building.comp;
  const buildingProps = building.props;
  return <BuildingComponent {...buildingProps} />;
}
&#8220;`
Now just imagine having to do this for 10 types of buildings. That switch statement would become hundreds of lines in mere seconds! This may be the simplest solution, but it&rsquo;s certainly ugly!</p>

<p>Enter React Router. React Router shows and hides content based on, you guessed it, routes. Usually, React Router is used for single page applications. You can show routes like /new, /edit, or /delete without actually having the entire application refresh. Instead, it simply shows the <code>New</code> component when the /new route is triggered.</p>

<p>Using React Router, we can simplify our code by using easy to understand <code>Routes</code> to dictate what Component and props we need.</p>

<p>First, we need a <code>Router</code>. There are many to choose from. <code>BrowserRouter</code> is what you&rsquo;d expect - it updates the browser&rsquo;s URL bar with a new route. It looks as if you&rsquo;ve actually navigated to a new page, even though the app does not actually reload from scratch. If you&rsquo;re building a React UI inside of another framework that already has routes, you obviously don&rsquo;t want to actually update the browser&rsquo;s URL bar. In that case, pick the <code>MemoryRouter</code>. Inside the <code>Router</code>, declare your routes like so:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">render() {
  return (
    &lt;MemoryRouter&gt;
      &lt;Route exact path="/house" component={House} /&gt;
      &lt;Route exact path="/museum" render = { (routeProps) =&gt; &lt;Museum {...routeProps} {...this.getMuseumProps()} /&gt;} /&gt;
    &lt;/MemoryRouter&gt;
  )
}
</code></pre>

<p>I&rsquo;ve provided two examples of how to declare a component in a <code>Route</code>. The first way is pretty straight forward. The <code>House</code> component does not need any props passed to it, so we can just use the component prop in <code>Route</code> and pass it the component&rsquo;s name. The route for /museum is a little different. In this case, we use the render prop. You always need to pass down information about the current route state - that&rsquo;s what <code>routeProps</code> is. But then you can append any other props that component might require. In this case, you can make small, manageable functions to return the props needed for specific components.</p>

<p>But wait. How do we actually switch routes? <code>Link</code> is the obvious component to use that comes built into React Router. You can look at their documentation for more information on that. In this example, we have some navigation tabs that calls an onClick method defined in the same component as our <code>Router</code>. How do we get the onClick method to change the route?</p>

<p>Step 1: Update the export default line-
&#8220;`javascript
import { withRouter } from &lsquo;react-router-dom&rsquo;;</p>

<p>class MainBuilding extends React.Component {
  &hellip;
}
export default withRouter(MainBuilding);
&#8220;`</p>

<p>Step 2: Change the route in the onClick method-
<code>javascript
class MainBuilding extends React.Component {
  ...
  onTabClick(newBuildingType) {
    const newRoutePath = `/${newTab}`;
    this.props.history.push(newRoutePath);
    this.setState({buildingType: newBuildingType});
  }
}
</code>
When we push the new route to history and update our state, our <code>render()</code> method is called and matches the new route. So, if the <code>newBuildingType</code> is &ldquo;house&rdquo;, then the component matching the route for <code>/house</code> will be displayed. Yes, you might have a lot of routes. But you can refactor this into still yet more manageable chunks, unlike a switch statement.</p>

<p>I hope this example helps you think about how to incorporate React Router into you app to better organize serving up specific components.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Speak Developer]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2017/03/02/i-speak-developer/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-02T21:46:45-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2017/03/02/i-speak-developer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I remember the days before I was a software engineer and I lived in a world where Python was a snake and not a programming language, where Java was just another word for coffee, and Cassandra was a person from Greek mythology. Most people live in my former world. If you talk to non-technical people about what you do - I mean, what you REALLY DO, no holds barred, describing all the tools and languages and processes you use every day - they will think you are speaking Klingon.</p>

<p>One of my coworkers set up a meeting with me next week because they wanted to better understand git branching and how it affects QA and production deployments. It took me a few months on the job after graduation to truly understand git. Local vs. remote, pushing, pulling, merging, branching, commits - it&rsquo;s confusing to most beginners. So, I feel like I really need to prepare for this meeting and think about how to explain aspects of git to someone on the outside. I thought that coming from a teaching background would help me describe to my non-technical coworkers about my daily challenges. Now I realize I am entrenched in tech-speak. I&rsquo;ve become the very person I didn&rsquo;t understand before starting my computer science degree.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Create Custom CSVs From jQuery Datatables]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/12/16/how-to-create-custom-csvs-from-jquery-datatables/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-16T09:59:05-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/12/16/how-to-create-custom-csvs-from-jquery-datatables</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s official! I&rsquo;ve been a software engineer who has been gainfully employed for more than <strong>1 year</strong>. And so, to celebrate, this post will be a technical one! Where I work, there&rsquo;s a scenario that pops up quite often:</p>

<blockquote><p>We&rsquo;d like to be able to export the data in a table located on <em>x</em> page of our application as a CSV file.</p></blockquote>

<p>It sounds simple enough. We use jQuery Datatables to generate most of the tables in our application. And of course, Datatables actually provides the ability to <a href="https://datatables.net/reference/button/csv">save the table as a CSV</a> or another file type. But unfortunately, there are some problems with using Datatables&#8217; built in CSV export:
1. Pagination: If you dynamically fill each page with data by making new ajax calls, then the CSV export will only export the active page, not all data.
2. You might want to include some data that&rsquo;s not displayed in the datatable, such as hidden values, or those used as part of a link for a row.</p>

<p>This is when you need to generate a custom CSV from your datatable. Here&rsquo;s the process:</p>

<ul>
<li>Create an export button near your datatable. Simple enough.</li>
<li>Next, you need to get the raw data. There are 2 ways to do this, depending on your situation. If there&rsquo;s no pagination and all of your data is contained in the datatable, you can simply do:</li>
</ul>


<pre><code>var dt = $("#idOfMyDatatable").DataTable();
var data = dt.rows().data();
</code></pre>

<p>If you&rsquo;re using pagination and need to retrieve all data, you can make an ajax request to your backend, probably to the same function you use to populate your datatable in the first place, but you can update it to retrieve all data by setting the <code>iDisplayLength</code> value to the <code>recordsDisplay</code> value. That&rsquo;s the total number of values in the table (The 100 in &lsquo;Viewing 1-10 of 100&rsquo;):</p>

<pre><code>var dt = $("#idOfMyDatatable").DataTable();
dt.on('init.dt', function(e) {
  var params = table.ajax.params();
  var iDisplayLength = dt.page.info().recordsDisplay;
  $.ajax({
    url: "/getDTJson/?iColumns=" + params.iColumns + "&amp;iDisplayStart=0&amp;iDisplayLength=" + iDisplayLength + "&amp;sSearch=" + params.sSearch,
    type: 'GET',
    success: function(data) {
      //This is our next step - working with the data. For now, you've retrieved it!
    }
    });
});
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>So, once we have our data, we can begin to craft our CSV file. We&rsquo;ll need to set up our basics like the headers and some basic file information. We&rsquo;ll also need to create an array, where each value is a line in the CSV.</li>
</ul>


<pre><code>var headings = ["Heading1", "Heading2", "Heading3"];
var lineArray = [];
lineArray.push("data:application/csv;charset=utf-8," + headings);
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li><p>Adding your actual data depends on how you retrieved your data in step 2.</p>

<ul>
<li>If you&rsquo;re getting your data from the datatable itself, ie: <code>var data = dt.rows().data();</code>, your data will look a little something like</li>
</ul>


<pre><code>{"0": ["value1", "value2", "value3", "value4"], "1":["value1", "value2", "value3", "value4"]}
</code></pre>

<p>You will need to loop through each array in the data object, pulling out only the values you want and storing those in a new array. If those values could possible contain a comma, make sure you escape them. Finally, join all values in your array into a string using a comma separator and store that string in your line array:</p>

<pre><code>for(var i = 0; i &lt; data.length; i++) {
  var lineWithSelectedValues = [];
  lineWithSelectedValues.push("\"" + data[i][0] + "\"");
  lineWithSelectedValues.push(data[i][2]);
  lineWithSelectedValues.push("\"" + data[i][3] + "\"");
  var csvLine = lineWithSelectedValues.join(",");
  lineArray.push(csvLine);
}
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>If you had to make a new ajax call to retrieve your data, your data will be in a two-dimensional array under the key <code>aaData</code>. Your data will look something like
<code>
{"aaData": [["value1", "value2", "value3", "value4"],["value1", "value2", "value3", "value4"]]}
</code>
You will need to loop through each nested array and extract only the values you want. Usually, I do this via a separate function, but for ease, I&rsquo;ll combine it into my code sample:</li>
</ul>


<pre><code class="``">  for (var i = 0; i &lt; data.aaData.length; i++) {
    var dataArray = data.aaData[i];
    var lineWithSelectedValues = [];
    lineWithSelectedValues.push("\"" + dataArray[0] + "\"");
    lineWithSelectedValues.push(dataArray[2]);
    lineWithSelectedValues.push("\"" + dataArray[3] + "\"");
    var csvLine = lineWithSelectedValues.join(",");
    lineArray.push(csvLine);
  }
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Our last step is to finalize our CSV content and hook up our export button to actually provide the ability to download the CSV. No matter how you got your data, you should have an array <code>var lineArray</code> that contains comma separated strings. We need to convert that to being just one string, with each string-row ending in a new line.</p></li>
</ul>


<pre><code>var csvContent = lineArray.join("\n");
var fileName = 'MyDatatbleCsv';
$("#exportBtn").attr({
  'href': encodeURI(csvContent),
  'download': fileName + '.csv',
  'target': '_blank'
  });
</code></pre>

<p>And there you have it! This is how I create a custom CSV from a datatable. I hope this helps you in your endeavors!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Right Stuff]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/06/29/the-right-stuff/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-29T17:53:22-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/06/29/the-right-stuff</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Building applications requires time, thoughtful planning, and the right tools to complete the task. There are so many programming languages and frameworks to choose from that sometimes I think people are overwhelmed by the &ldquo;possibilities.&rdquo;</p>

<p>At work, we use Scala and Play Framework. Normally, those who come from a Java background are supposed to be amazed by the versatility of Scala. I come from a Java background. I am not impressed. I don&rsquo;t <em>hate</em> Scala, but it&rsquo;s a struggle to use because it is poorly documented. The massive amount of collections, both mutable and immutable, is not a feature. I&rsquo;m constantly using the REPL to determine how to add, delete, and retrieve values from the whole host of Scala collections. It&rsquo;s not intuitive. Scala is like an elitist programming language. It&rsquo;s like its creators decided, &ldquo;Oh, you&rsquo;d like to learn Scala? That&rsquo;s great! Best of luck to you!&rdquo; and then idly stand by and laugh as you try to make sense of it all. I even own a book on Scala and even it is ambiguous at best on many &ldquo;features&rdquo; of Scala.</p>

<p>Now on to Play Framework, which is even worse than Scala itself. I&rsquo;m pretty much a pro at application frameworks. I&rsquo;ve used Ruby on Rails, Dropwizard (Java), Django (Python), Node.js, and probably a few more that I&rsquo;m forgetting right now. I&rsquo;ll admit that Play&rsquo;s backend functionality&hellip;you know, models and controllers, are rather straight forward. If you actually know Scala or Java (though Play seems to discourage using Java), you&rsquo;re all set. But when it comes to writing a front-end? Good luck!</p>

<p>I spent almost 2 weeks on building a view that should have taken 2 days. I wanted a rather simple form and Play&rsquo;s Form generation seemed like the way to go. It has validation on the backend, serializes to a model, and all that good stuff. Unfortunately, many use cases just do not conform to Play&rsquo;s idea of a form. I wanted radio button displayed vertically. Play said NO. I wanted radio buttons that looked like buttons (no circle to click on&hellip;instead, the button background should change when clicked). Play has no means of doing that. It says you can create your own inputs, but that&rsquo;s in the <em>singular</em> and obviously, I wanted multiple radio buttons. I asked for help on StackOverflow and even in the Play Framework Google group. <strong>CRICKETS.</strong> If you use this framework, you are on your own to figure out how to use it. The documentation lacks full descriptions of how to do basic things and there&rsquo;s no community for help.</p>

<p>In the end, I was put out my misery and wrote the front-end in pure HTML with some jQuery and Parsley for validation. And it took me barely a few hours to get everything working! Just because something is there doesn&rsquo;t mean it&rsquo;s the right tool. Sometimes, if you know something is just easier to work with, saves time, and the result will be easier to maintain in the long run, that&rsquo;s what you should choose.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What It Means to Be in Tech]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/05/25/what-it-means-to-be-intech/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-25T08:14:05-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/05/25/what-it-means-to-be-intech</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many people claim to be &lsquo;in tech.&rsquo; There is a prestigious connotation about it. It means being at the cutting edge of something great, being in demand and desirable, and being well-off among other positives associated with the tech industry. The tech industry continues to boom, with <a href="http://www.usatoday.com/story/money/markets/2016/05/20/third-cash-owned-5-us-companies/84640704/">USA Today</a> reporting that 5 major tech companies hold a third of all US cash, not financial firms! No wonder people want to be associated with tech!</p>

<p>My definition of someone in tech is narrow. I believe it is a person who has a technical background( science, technology, engineering, and mathematics) who directly uses that education and experience in their everyday responsibilities. In other words, if they have an engineering education, they should <em>actually</em> be doing engineering work.</p>

<p>Needless to say, I am absolutely frustrated when people, especially women, are labeled as &lsquo;women in tech.&rsquo; I understand that people are trying to make tech more appealing to women by showing successful women in the field. But articles like Elle Magazine&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.elle.com/culture/tech/g8676/most-influential-women-in-technology/">Most Influential Women in Technology</a> are misleading. Only 2 of the individuals listed actually have some education in a STEM field. Most are entrepreneurs or occupy some upper management role. They are not doing anything technical! Therefore, I argue they are not in tech! It&rsquo;s like saying the janitor at a local high school is in education. They&rsquo;re not!</p>

<p>This far extends beyond labeling women as being in the tech industry, though. There are plenty of people labeling themselves as being part of the tech industry on LinkedIn, but take a look at their education and it&rsquo;s usually some business or finance degree. Just because they may work for a tech company does not mean they are &lsquo;in tech.&rsquo;</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s time to use this label only for those who actually do true technical work! By allowing those without a technical degree and role to assume the label of &lsquo;in tech&rsquo; degrades what it means to be an engineer or a scientist. For women, it is even more detrimental because the aspirational models set before them are still not true women in STEM roles. It sends the message, &ldquo;Yes, you can be in tech and no, you don&rsquo;t have to major in engineering or science to do it!&rdquo; So, be wary the next time someone claims to be &lsquo;in tech.&rsquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Change in Scenery]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/05/19/a-change-in-scenery/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-19T18:38:54-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/05/19/a-change-in-scenery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started a new job in the beginning of April. My first job as a software engineer, though, will always have a special spot in my heart. I accepted my first software engineering role because a) I&rsquo;d be working for a well-known company with a prominent reputation in the tech space and b) I really needed some hands-on experience. My only experience prior to my first job was a summer internship at a start-up, where I really had no clue what the heck was going on. <em>&ldquo;What&rsquo;s an API?&rdquo;</em> Haha! There&rsquo;s quite a gap between learning software development in a university classroom and actually building applications for a business.</p>

<h3>My First Job</h3>

<p>My first job served its purpose. I am very proud of the projects I completed, the technologies I learned on the job, and the social skills I acquired in order to deploy my work. Seriously, social skills in the office are highly underrated! I leaned on my co-workers a lot so I could understand how to do Jenkins deployments, merging changes in Github, and running applications in Docker containers. My boss was very hands-off. He generally told me what to build and it was up to me to build it. I was a very competent developer, though. UPenn and my true mentor (my husband) prepared me well and I made short work of most of my projects! After a month or so into the job, my boss trusted me enough to allow me to select which technologies to use for my projects. I became an AngularJS master! I was really grateful that I was able to do full-stack development there. Some people like front-end dev, others like back-end, but I&rsquo;ve never wanted to choose between the two. I like the challenges of both.</p>

<h3>Honest Job Searching</h3>

<p>If your first job is your dream job, you&rsquo;re probably very, very lucky! While I liked my first job, there were some hard truths that I&rsquo;d come to realize as I sat in my cubicle. What makes a fulfilling career? I wanted my next job to make me really happy to come to work. I didn&rsquo;t want just a paycheck. I&rsquo;m giving up 40+ hours of my life every week and I wanted those 40+ hours to count for something other than dollars. My first job was really just a job. I wasn&rsquo;t unhappy, but I wasn&rsquo;t exactly joyful either. There was a slowdown of projects and I was bored. I knew that I wanted my next job to have lots of work to keep me busy and engaged! I also wanted the option to work from home. I really hated that office. I had a terribly uncomfortable chair, noisy cubicle neighbors, and I felt alone in the cubicle maze. Software development is a pretty sweet career - it CAN be done at home. And I wanted to be in the comfort of my home some days, sitting on my comfortable couch in the peaceful quiet thoughtfully writing code. When I earnestly started my job search, I told my recruiter that I was looking for a full-stack position with the ability to work from home. And she found a great company for me!</p>

<h3>My New Job</h3>

<p>I can&rsquo;t say enough good things about where I am right now! I think I&rsquo;m the happiest I&rsquo;ve ever been! I truly <em>LOVE</em> my new job! The people I work with are really fun people. There&rsquo;s a nice culture in the office where people say hello to one another in the morning, chat casually in Slack, and go out to lunch together! It&rsquo;s an open office, which I thought I would come to hate, but it&rsquo;s actually grown on me. I truly feel like I&rsquo;m part of the team (♪♪ everything is awesome&hellip;. ♪♪). The product I&rsquo;m improving and building out is <em>really</em> interesting and has a lot going for it! I&rsquo;m definitely challenged by the large codebase and I celebrate every time I fix a bug or make an improvement. Raising my hands in victory a few times a week feels very, very good! I work from home some days and that&rsquo;s really improved my quality of life. I can really get in the zone at home. There&rsquo;s no need for putting on headphones with white noise playing in the background. And it&rsquo;s also nice to &lsquo;work&rsquo; with my favorite coding partner: my dog!</p>

<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>

<p>If you&rsquo;re just starting out in software engineering, don&rsquo;t be discouraged by being told you don&rsquo;t have enough experience. An opportunity will come your way and you&rsquo;ll make the best of it. When you&rsquo;re ready to move on, be honest about what you want. It <em>is</em> achievable!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Kinesis FreeStyle2]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/02/24/the-kinesis-freestyle2/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-24T20:24:50-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/02/24/the-kinesis-freestyle2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://LCBecker.github.io/images/freestyle.jpg" title="kinesis keyboard" alt="kinesis keyboard"></p>

<p>So, how&rsquo;s my new Kinesis FreeStyle2 keyboard? Is it as ergonomical as I need it to be relieve my RSI symptoms? Would it work well for you? Read on!</p>

<h3>Day 1</h3>

<p>I started my work day setting up the FreeStyle2 with the the VIP3 accessory kit. It took about 10 minutes, because I actually read directions :-P The wrist rests and the lifts snapped in nice and easy! I decided to use the largest angle, 15 degrees, for the lift. The more vertical it is, the more like that handshake position that&rsquo;s supposed to be ideal.</p>

<h4>Benefits of a Split Keyboard</h4>

<p>There are so many benefits of having a split keyboard. For one, my arms were so much more relaxed. Not only did it help my arms, but my back as well!</p>

<p>One surprising benefit of the split keyboard: the space in the middle! I was able to put my steno pad front and center! No longer was it off to the side so I&rsquo;d have to keep pivoting to look at my notes!</p>

<h4>Hotkey Blunder</h4>

<p>One of the things I was really looking forward having on the FreeStyle2 were the special keys on the left key panel. There are a variety of hotkeys including copy, paste, and select all. No more Command+C! So, as I was working, I found myself in situations that required copying and pasting text. Time to use the hotkeys! So, I highlighted some text, pressed the Copy hotkey&hellip;.and heard a &ldquo;ERRRR&rdquo; noise out of my headphones. I started pressing a variety of hotkeys and each one did not do as it was expected. One of the keys put Google Chrome in background mode (who knew Chome had such a thing as background mode?) and the others force quit some of my applications! YIKES!</p>

<p>I searched online, but no one reported issues with this keyboard&rsquo;s hotkeys. That could only mean one thing: Dvorak. I switched over to the Dvorak-Qwerty setting on my Mac and TA DA, the hotkeys worked!!!</p>

<h3>Week 1+</h3>

<p>Well, it&rsquo;s been one week of using my Kinesis keyboard. Some things have definitely changed since Day 1. Let&rsquo;s review:</p>

<h4>Goodbye, Hotkeys</h4>

<p>The hotkeys are still buggy. Really buggy. After switching to Dvorak-Qwerty, they worked, but only in certain applications. They didn&rsquo;t work in my main code editor, Eclipse. The applications where they did work made other Command+keys stopped working––one of which was the all important Command+S (Save). In my Atom editor, I apparently re-assigned keypresses by pressing Command+S. OOPS! Needless to say, I decided to go back to regular Dvorak, making the hotkeys useless again. At least I can actually save my work now.</p>

<h4>Tilt Good? Tilt Bad?</h4>

<p>I can&rsquo;t decide whether the 15 degree tilt is comfortable or not. I&rsquo;ve been experimenting now with the 10 degree tilt. I&rsquo;m not sure whether it&rsquo;s actually beneficial. The jury is still out on this one.</p>

<h4>Where Should My Mouse Go?</h4>

<p>I think this is the most fundamentally troubling question I&rsquo;ve been trying to answer this past week. The split keyboard makes my arms nice and comfortable, but only when <strong>typing</strong>. But my mouse is farther away, meaning I need to lean over to do all my clicking, moving of arrows, and scrolling. After a day or two of my new configuration, my right shoulder was really uncomfortable.</p>

<p>For a few days, I tried putting my mouse in the middle, between the two keyboard pads. But this is sadly also uncomfortable. It kind of negates the reason why I wanted a split keyboard in the first place&hellip;so my arms would not be at some unnatural angle in front of my body.</p>

<p>Lately, I&rsquo;ve tried doing as much as I can via the keyboard. I&rsquo;ve started learning the keypresses needed to toggle between tabs and applications. I&rsquo;ve used the page-down keys more for scrolling down on webpages. It&rsquo;s better than constantly reaching for the mouse. But the mouse is still essential and it&rsquo;s hard to know what else I can do to make using it more comfortable.</p>

<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m still very happy with my Kinesis FreeStyle2 purchase.</p>

<p><strong>PROS:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>It really has helped a lot with my wrist, arm, shoulder and finger pain.</li>
<li>That space in between the keypads is great for a notebook!</li>
<li>There&rsquo;s no learning curve to use it. It&rsquo;s a regular keyboard, just in a split configuration!</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>CONS:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Your mouse will be further away due to the split. There&rsquo;s probably no place to put your mouse in a comfortable position. You&rsquo;ll need to try learning more key shortcuts to do things you&rsquo;d normally do with your mouse so you don&rsquo;t need to reach for your mouse as much.</li>
<li>If you type in Dvorak, the hotkeys are useless.</li>
</ul>


<p>Thanks for reading!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Time for a New Keyboard]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/02/16/a-rant-about-ergonomics/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-16T17:10:38-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/02/16/a-rant-about-ergonomics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://LCBecker.github.io/images/kinesis.jpg" title="kinesis keyboard" alt="kinesis keyboard"></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about ergonomics lately. A few weeks ago, I thought I was dreaming as I looked down and saw that my little finger&rsquo;s bone had somehow managed to overlap my ring finger&rsquo;s bone. My hand looked like a claw! I had to use my other hand to set my finger bones back in shape.</p>

<p>I knew I had to do something. I love software engineering, but let&rsquo;s face it––it&rsquo;s sort of a crippling job. Sitting all day: Not good. Typing/mousing all day: Not good.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve written <a href="http://lcbecker.github.io/blog/2014/11/13/why-i-type-in-dvorak/">before</a> about how switching to Dvorak helped alleviate my RSI. But clearly, it was back. A simple search discovered that the Apple Magic Bluetooth keyboard is absolutely AWFUL for RSI. Time for a new keyboard&hellip;</p>

<h3>Ye Old Keyboard</h3>

<p>First, I brought my old Logitech keyboard to work. This poor keyboard has been sitting collecting dust in front of my desktop (which was last turned on&hellip;hmm&hellip;3 years ago?). Right away, there was a problem––the number pad on the right. I felt like my mouse was so far away and my right arm was forced to be at a 60 degree angle from my body to type. Awkward!</p>

<h3>The Kinesis Classic QD</h3>

<p>Thankfully, a friend allowed me to borrow his Kinesis Classic QD keyboard (pictured above) to get a feel for it. He swears by it after suffering himself from RSI and has been using it for years! This is probably one of the strangest keyboards I&rsquo;ve ever seen, but it has a lot going for it. The wrist pads are perfectly positioned. The inset wells for the keys puts your fingers at a natural downward tilt. And what I loved most of all––the division between left and right puts your arms perpendicular to your body, which is way more comfortable than having them angled to the middle of your body! It also has the keys you probably press the most pushed to the thumb regions. The keys can be remapped in whatever configuration you prefer.</p>

<p>After trying the Kinesis Classic (newer versions are called the <a href="https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/shop/advantage-for-pc-mac/">Advantage</a>) for a week, it was clear what I loved and hated about this keyboard. And what I hated was the key configurations. I have tiny hands, so using any of the thumb buttons was actually putting a lot of strain on my wrists to twist and reach those buttons. Even though I could remap keys, it was really difficult getting used to pressing keys that I was used to being placed in areas of the keyboard that no longer existed in the Kinesis key layout. Yet, this trial run was enough to convince me that Kinesis was on to something&hellip;</p>

<h3>The Kinesis FreeStyle2</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ll write a post about my experiences with this keyboard once I get it later this week. However, I think the Kinesis <a href="https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/shop/freestyle2-for-mac/">FreeStyle2</a> has everything I loved about the Classic without all the things I disliked. I bought the 20&#8221; extension for that great left/right arm separation. I also purchased the optional VIP3 accessory package that allows you to vertically tilt the keyboard. Supposedly, the &ldquo;handshake&rdquo; position is better for your wrists and arms. If you have pain in your lower arm, this might be great for you. The VIP3 also comes with Kinesis&#8217; awesome wrist pads (seriously, they&rsquo;re worth raving about!).</p>

<p><em>Stay Tuned For More On My Journey into Being More Ergonomical!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interactive SVGs in AngularJS]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/12/18/interactive-svgs-in-angularjs/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-18T18:28:47-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/12/18/interactive-svgs-in-angularjs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://LCBecker.github.io/images/dvorak.jpg" title="Dvorak keyboard" alt="Dvorak keyboard"></p>

<p>My latest project has been utilizing my art degree (wait, what? An art degree is useful as a software engineer? Surprisingly, YES). Using Inkscape, I created a very customized keyboard as an SVG (Scalable Vector Graphic). There were two things I had to do with this file:</p>

<ol>
<li>Embed the SVG into a view inside my AngularJS application.</li>
<li>Each key element/node needed an <code>ng-click</code> attribute so when it was pressed, something would happen. Because, you know, what good is a key if you can&rsquo;t click on it?</li>
</ol>


<p>As I discovered, these two tasks are a lot harder than they should be. Putting an SVG into a view is as simple as making the file path the <code>data</code> of an <code>&lt;object&gt;</code> in the HTML. You can add an <code>ng-click</code> to the <code>&lt;object&gt;</code>, but that only works if you want the entire SVG to be clickable. I wanted interactivity <em>inside</em> the SVG itself. Adding <code>ng-click</code> as an attribute within a node in the SVG file will NOT work! To do what I wanted, I neede to use directives to embed the SVG in the view and attach a <code>ng-click</code> attribute to each of my keys.</p>

<p>I found <a href="" title="https://goo.gl/3s3Vlu">this site</a> that had an interactive map and thought, &ldquo;Hey, that&rsquo;s kind of similar to what I want to do!&rdquo; So, using their insights, I was able to make a clickable keyboard within my AngularJS application. Here&rsquo;s how I did it:</p>

<h3>Add A Class and Unique ID to SVG Nodes</h3>

<p>My keys were mainly circle elements with some text on top. I flattened my SVG to one layer to ensure that when a user clicked anywhere inside the circle element, it would trigger a click event. I added a class to each circle element and also updated the id of each circle element to reference its value, like so:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;circle
    r="43"
    cy="569"
    cx="227"
    style="fill:#4d4d4d;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:3"
    id="btn_MENU"
    class="boardKeys" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<h3>Make Two Directives</h3>

<p>I just put both directives in the same file: keyDirectives.js.</p>

<p>Directive One: Embed the SVG.</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">var myApp = angular.module('KeyboardAppModule');

myApp.directive('svgKeys', ['$compile', function($compile) {
    return {
        restrict: 'A',
        templateUrl: 'images/keyboard.svg',
        link: function(scope, element, attrs) {
            var keys = element[0].querySelectorAll('.boardKeys');
            angular.forEach(keys, function(path, key) {
            var myKey = angular.element(path);
            myKey.attr("myKey", "");
            $compile(myKey)(scope);
            })
        }
    }
}]);
</code></pre>

<p>Notice these details: <code>var keys</code> is an array of all elements with the class <code>boardKeys</code>&hellip;the same class I attached to each circle element (key) inside my SVG. For each of these circles, the directive adds the attribute <code>myKey</code> which is really the name of Directive Two. Directive Two is then initiated. But first, since I now have the directive that places the SVG into the view, take a look at the view&rsquo;s HTML:</p>

<pre><code class="html">    &lt;div class="row"&gt;
        &lt;div class="col-sm-8 col-sm-offset-2"&gt;
            &lt;div svgKeys&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>See how I just threw that directive in there? That&rsquo;ll just embed the SVG in that div! Woohoo! But wait, I still need to register clicking a key.</p>

<p>Directive Two: Add <code>ng-click</code> to all keys.</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">myApp.directive('myKey', ['$compile', function($compile) {
    return {
        restrict: 'A',
        scope: true,
        link: function (scope, element, attrs) {
            scope.elementId = element.attr("id");
            scope.keyClick = function() {
                scope.pressKey(scope.elementId);
            };
            element.attr("ng-click", "keyClick()");
            element.removeAttr("myKey");
            $compile(element)(scope);
        }
    }
}]);
</code></pre>

<p>So, Directive One added the <code>myKey</code> directive to each key, which then calls Directive Two, which adds the <code>ng-click</code> attribute to each key. For me, I used a function called <code>pressKey()</code> in my controller. It&rsquo;s accessible via scope and I felt that my controller is where someone would look to see what happens when a button is clicked. You could just as well define what should happen when a key is clicked here in the directive. Also notice that I pass <code>scope.elementId</code> to my <code>pressKey</code> function. <code>scope.elementId</code> is the key&rsquo;s ID! So, now I know <em>which</em> key was clicked and can handle the case as needed!</p>

<h3>FIN</h3>

<p>It obviously doesn&rsquo;t take a lot of code to make an SVG file&rsquo;s elements interactive in Angular, but it&rsquo;s certainly not intuitive. Nonetheless, it&rsquo;s great that this code works and I&rsquo;m excited for my next Angular application with interactive SVGs!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DropWizard Metrics 101]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/11/18/dropwizard-metrics-101/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-18T18:18:54-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/11/18/dropwizard-metrics-101</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://LCBecker.github.io/images/metrics.jpg" title="metrics art" alt="metrics art"></p>

<h6>IO Graph Art by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/nathanmac87/4415951740">nathanmac87</a></h6>

<p><strong>Post revised 11/23/2015 for correctness. Thank you to Jan-Olav Eide and Tim Bart for leading me in the right direction!</strong></p>

<p>My most recent project at work has been to utilize DropWizard metrics to gather information about an application I built and send that data to Graphite to display in a realtime dashboard. As I normally do, I reviewed the documentation for <a href="https://dropwizard.github.io/metrics/3.1.0/getting-started/">Dropwizard Metrics</a>, but as usual, there was a lot to be desired. Their example did not go into the nitty gritty of <em>how</em> to connect everything together. The internet was also silent on how to actually use DropWizard metrics.</p>

<p>So here is my tutorial on how <em>I</em> was able to get DropWizard metrics up and running in my application:</p>

<h3>1. Maven Application? Update pom.xml</h3>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve got a Maven application, you&rsquo;ll need to add metrics-core as a dependency. If you&rsquo;re using some sort of special reporter like Graphite, you may need to add additional dependencies. This was what I had to add to my pom:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;io.dropwizard.metrics&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;metrics-core&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;3.1.0&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;
&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;io.dropwizard.metrics&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;metrics-graphite&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;3.1.0&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;
&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;io.dropwizard&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;dropwizard-metrics-graphite&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;0.9.1&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;
</code></pre>

<h3>2. Start Your Metrics On Application Startup</h3>

<p>Supposedly, there are two ways you can initialize your metrics reporters. A reporter sends your data to either the console, logger, Graphite, or other DropWizard-approved outputs. You can either specify them in your config.yml file, as seen <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/29432586/dropwizard-yaml-for-graphite-server-configuration">here</a>. This is supposed to start reporting your metrics automatically when you start your application. I tried this method, but I had zero luck with it. I ended up getting some parsing error from within DropWizard&rsquo;s validation library.</p>

<p>So, I initialized my metrics an alternative way&ndash; in the <code>run()</code> method of my application class. DropWizard&rsquo;s environment already creates a <code>MetricRegistry</code> object on startup. This object manages all of our metrics (these are timers, counters, meters, histograms, and gauges). Since I added metrics to my resources class, I needed to pass that <code>MetricRegistry</code> object to my resource class. This is how my application class looked:</p>

<pre><code>public class MyApplication extends Application&lt;MyConfiguration&gt;{

    public static void main(String[] args) throws Exception {
        new MyApplication().run(args);
    }

    @Override
    public void run(MyConfiguration config, Environment env) throws Exception {

        final Graphite graphite = new Graphite(new InetSocketAddress("my.graphite.host", 2003));

        final GraphiteReporter reporter = GraphiteReporter.forRegistry(env.metrics())
            .prefixedWith("upToYou")
            .convertRatesTo(TimeUnit.SECONDS)
            .convertDurationsTo(TimeUnit.MILLISECONDS)
            .filter(MetricFilter.ALL)
            .build(graphite);
        reporter.start(5, TimeUnit.SECONDS);
        environment.jersey().register(new MyResource(env.metrics()));
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Some things to note: The <code>prefixedWith</code> is not required. What this does is append a label in front of our metrics names. I&rsquo;ll explain this more in Step 3.</p>

<h3>3. Add Metrics To Your Resources</h3>

<p>I wanted metrics like &lsquo;How many requests are we getting at /path1&rsquo; and &lsquo;How long is it taking for the method handling /path1 to return a response&rsquo;. Chances are you are, too. In order to do this, we&rsquo;ll need to add metrics to our resources. And those metrics need to be &ldquo;saved&rdquo; in the <code>MetricRegistry</code> from Step 2. So we&rsquo;ll need to create a constructor for our resource that will take in the <code>MetricRegistry</code> object we passed in Step 2.</p>

<p>There are two ways to add metrics to your resources: using annotations and by actually creating objects of a metrics class. I&rsquo;ll give you an example of both:</p>

<pre><code>public class MyResource {
     MetricRegistry metrics;
     Meter requestCount;

     public MyResource(MetricRegistry registry) {
        this.metrics = registry;
        requestCount = metrics.meter(MetricRegister.name("requestCount"));
     }

     @POST
     @Path("/path1")
     @Produces(MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN)
     @Timed(absolute=true, name="requestRuntime")
     public Response handleRequest() {
        requestCount.mark();
        return Response.ok("Hello World").build(); //you know what I mean...
     }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Notice these details:</p>

<ul>
<li>We declare the meter <code>requestCount</code>, which will give us the total count of all calls made to /path1 and how many requests /path1 gets in 1 minute, 5 minute, and 15 minute timeframes. We initialized this <code>Meter</code> object in our Resource constructor, It&rsquo;s initialization uses our <code>MetricRegistry</code> so it can manage it accordingly.</li>
<li>See the <code>@Timed</code> annotation? DropWizard will automatically create a timer and whenever <code>handleRequest()</code> is called, the timer will record how long it takes to complete this method. We do not need to initialize a timer object ourselves. We can name this timer. I&rsquo;ve added the <code>absolute=true</code> field, because otherwise, the entire path of this metric in Graphite will be my prefix + package path + class + requestRuntime. Too long! By setting absolute to true, the metric path is just the prefix + the metric name.</li>
<li>Remember in Step 2 when we saw that <code>.prefixedWith("upToYou")</code>? Basically, our reporter, whether Graphite or the console or something else, will refer to this metric by the prefix + name of the metric. Graphite showed me options to graph like, &ldquo;upToYou.requestCount.count&rdquo; and &ldquo;upToYou.requestCount.mean&rdquo; (the &lsquo;count&rsquo; and &lsquo;mean&rsquo; part are automatically attached by DropWizard metrics). You don&rsquo;t need any prefix, but if you want it, go for it back in Step 2.</li>
<li>Finally, we call our meter&rsquo;s <code>mark()</code> method. That tells the metric, &ldquo;Hey, the method we&rsquo;re tracking has been called! Increment the meter count!&rdquo; The <code>mark()</code> method is for the meter metric, though. Please refer to the <a href="https://dropwizard.github.io/metrics/3.1.0/getting-started/">DropWizard Metrics</a> documentation on how to initialize and call counters, histograms, and other metrics. Now, here we&rsquo;ve programmatically called the meter&rsquo;s method. We don&rsquo;t have to do that. We could just use the annotation <code>@Metered(absolute=true, name="myMeter")</code> and DropWizard would automatically call <code>mark()</code> for us whenever our method was called. But this is how you would do it if you wanted additional control&hellip;or multiple meters on a single method.</li>
</ul>


<h3>4. Profit</h3>

<p>Now, when we start up our application, our metrics will be monitoring what we want and sending data to the console or Graphite or wherever!</p>

<p>So, there you have it! This is how everything ties together in DropWizard Metrics! And I&rsquo;m the first person to actually write an example of this! Woohoo! I hope you have enjoyed this post and that it&rsquo;s given you a decent amount of confidence to use DropWizard metrics in your application! Happy Coding!</p>

<p>If you really like this, tell me on Twitter @LBeckerCodes !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HTTPS With Jersey]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/10/26/https-with-jersey/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-26T20:16:51-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/10/26/https-with-jersey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am so excited about this post! It&rsquo;s a technical post! With code! I wanted to write this to help others who might find themselves in the same predicament.</p>

<p>This was the issue: I&rsquo;m writing a DropWizard application. DropWizard uses Jersey. My application needed to take in a POST request and use the post body to make a POST request to a trusted server using HTTPS. But then this error showed up:</p>

<pre><code>ERROR [2015-10-22 20:41:23,405] io.dropwizard.jersey.errors.LoggingExceptionMapper: Error handling a request: 8d10b79e51bbb14d
! java.lang.IllegalStateException: AlreadyConnected
! at sun.net.www.protocol.http.HttpsUrlConnection.setRequestProperty(Unknown Source)...
</code></pre>

<p>After doing a little Googling, I found out that the exception is mislabeled. Jersey shouldn&rsquo;t be throwing an IllegalStateException. It should be a SSLHandshakeException. Ok, so the question is: What&rsquo;s the workaround? We need to get Jersey (version 2) to accept a self-signed SSL certificate. This requires creating a class with a method we can call to help build a client with the needed configurations. I created this class exactly as Aleksandr Panzin demonstrated <a href="https://gist.github.com/JAlexoid/b15dba31e5919586ae51">here</a>.</p>

<p>Once I added the <code>JerseyWithSSL</code> class, I realized, &ldquo;Hey, Aleksandr didn&rsquo;t explain how to actually use it!&rdquo; And so now, I provide to you the complete solution! Back in my resources class, I created a client using the <code>JerseyWithSSL</code> method <code>initClient()</code>:</p>

<pre><code>import java.security.KeyManagementException;
import java.security.NoSuchAlgorithmException;
import javax.ws.rs.POST;
import javax.ws.rs.client.Client;
import org.glassfish.jersey.client.ClientConfig;

@Path("/ticket")
public class Ticket

@POST
public Response createTicket(...) {
    ClientConfig cc = new ClientConfig();
    Client client = null;
    try {
        client = new JerseyWithSSL().initClient(cc);
    } catch (KeyManagementException e) {
        e.printStackTrace();
    } catch (NoSuchAlgorithmException e) { 
        e.printStackTrace();
    }

// Use client as you need...
</code></pre>

<p>The trick was figuring out what exactly the <code>Configuration</code> parameter was supposed to be in the <code>initClient()</code> method. An instance of <code>ClientConfig</code> did the trick. I&rsquo;m happy to say my application works due to this code! Hopefully, it will help you if you ever come across this error.</p>

<p>Happy Coding!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It's My First Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/10/01/its-my-first-day/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-01T20:17:11-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/10/01/its-my-first-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m writing this blog post for women who aspire to be software engineers. What is it like on your first day on the job as a software engineer? This is my experience:</p>

<h4>EXCITING!</h4>

<p>I worked hard to get here. I thought graduation day was great, but my first day on the job was truly the reward. Walking into that office this morning was a very proud moment! I love all the firsts of a first day: a new computer, a new workspace, a new project, meeting new people, getting that badge to get in and out of the building (with my face on it!). It was very exciting and made the day fly by!</p>

<h4>CONFUSED!</h4>

<p>I&rsquo;m pretty sure that from large corporation to small startup, acronyms are consistently thrown around. On my first day, as we did our daily standup meeting and then a &ldquo;here&rsquo;s an overview of this project,&rdquo; all I could think about was counting up all the acronyms. Every department has an acronym, our project title is an acronym, and let&rsquo;s face it, everything in computer science is an acronym (XML, JSON, REST, API,&hellip;). I accepted that, in time, I&rsquo;d learn who/what all these acronyms stood for.</p>

<h4>SMART!</h4>

<p>Yeah, I did feel pretty smart. I looked through source code, writing down the classes, how they connect, what they (seemingly) do&hellip;and I felt capable! I felt I was trained pretty well at reading code, understanding it, how to look up things I wasn&rsquo;t sure about&hellip;it was great!</p>

<p>My first day on the job as a software engineer was all I hoped it would be. I&rsquo;ll report on my first week in my next blog post!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Graduated. Now What?]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/07/20/i-graduated-now-what/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-20T16:57:04-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/07/20/i-graduated-now-what</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://LCBecker.github.io/images/PennDiploma.jpg" title="UPenn Diploma" alt="UPenn Diploma"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s official. I&rsquo;ve earned my Master&rsquo;s in Computer and Information Technology. It&rsquo;s a wonderful and strange feeling. I certainly went out of my comfort zone, learned a new skill set, and loved every minute of it. But of course, I&rsquo;m not done learning yet.</p>

<p>While I&rsquo;ve been job hunting, I&rsquo;ve been trying to learn new programming languages while strengthening the ones I know. To be honest, there really isn&rsquo;t one aspect of development that I love over another. I love coding the full stack. I honestly don&rsquo;t care what programming language I&rsquo;m using either (well&hellip;as long as it&rsquo;s not C). I stumbled upon <a href="www.codeeval.com">CodeEval</a>, a website full of programming problems. I decided to do at least one problem each day. At first, I was only doing the problems in Java since that&rsquo;s my strongest language. According to my CodeEval <a href="https://www.codeeval.com/profile/LBecker/">profile</a>, I&rsquo;m one of the top 15% Java developers sitewide (out of 6,000+)! Then I realized this would be a great way to get better at coding in other languages I&rsquo;m interested in. So besides a not-so-little side project in Python/Flask, I decided to start solving CodeEval problems in Python. It&rsquo;s taught me a lot of the ins-and-outs of Python. I really get a kick out of successfully solving some of these intricate coding problems!</p>

<p>As I said earlier, I&rsquo;m not partial to front-end or back-end development. I truly enjoy doing both. While looking at job descriptions, it seemed to me that many companies might actually benefit from having someone like me - someone who can code Java one day, and JavaScript the next. JavaScript and I have a funny history. Sometimes I love it (you know, when it works) and sometimes I hate it (let&rsquo;s face it - sometimes JS forces you to write ugly code). But with all the frameworks to choose from, JavaScript can be tolerable, even enjoyable. I enrolled in <a href="http://www.freecodecamp.com">Free Code Camp</a>. Supposedly, it takes a year to complete, but I&rsquo;m already more than half way through and I just started 2 weeks ago. It was a good brush-up on HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, and jQuery. I completed all the JavaScript lessons (through <a href="http://www.codecademy.com">Codecademy</a>) and now I&rsquo;m doing JavaScript &ldquo;bonfires&rdquo; (through Free Code Camp): programming problems to get you familiar with common built-in functions like Array.split(), filter, etc.</p>

<p>As I started completing the JavaScript bonfires, I thought to myself, &ldquo;Hmm, wouldn&rsquo;t it be fun to try to solve CodeEval problems in JavaScript?&rdquo;. So I tried&hellip;and I was able to do it! I&rsquo;m the only one in Philadelphia who has solved any CodeEval problem in JavaScript! <strong>I AM THE FIRST!</strong> Currently, I&rsquo;m in 11th place on the Philadelphia All-Time Leaderboard. I plan on getting into the Top 10 this week.</p>

<p>So that&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;ve been doing since I graduated: Improving. Job hunting. I hope the job hunting will end soon, though. As much fun as I&rsquo;m having learning on my own, it&rsquo;s nothing compared to when you&rsquo;re completing a <em>real</em> project with <em>real</em> requirements for a <em>real</em> client. Hopefully my next blog post will be about my first day as a software engineer! Until next time!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Graduation in T-Minus 12 Days]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/05/04/graduation-in-t-minus-12-days/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-04T16:46:46-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/05/04/graduation-in-t-minus-12-days</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://LCBecker.github.io/images/2015grad.jpg" alt="The Graduate" />
It&rsquo;s been a very long time since I&rsquo;ve updated this blog, so let me fill you in:</p>

<p>CIS 555: I have nearly completed one of the hardest courses in computer science at The University of Pennsylvania. And I&rsquo;ve done really well, even though I totally struggled with some of the assignments (we have to implement what now?). Struggling is good. Struggling means you&rsquo;re learning something. In 4 days, my group and I will demo our search engine that we wrote from the ground up. If we ever get it working in full (fingers crossed!). I was assigned to do the Search Engine and web interface, which is great for me. I like doing a litte bit of everything. I designed the front-end and I do a great job of communicating with databases in AWS to get results, rank them, and display them. I&rsquo;m proud of my code. It&rsquo;s tested, commented, and it works!</p>

<p>Philly Women In Tech Conference: I went to it after I snagged a free ticket. I&rsquo;m really glad I didn&rsquo;t pay for that ticket, because the conference was terrible. There are a lot of women who want to be grouped into the &ldquo;Women In Tech&rdquo; label because, let&rsquo;s face it, that&rsquo;s a pretty sweet label to have. I do believe, however, that women who work for a tech company in a capacity other than engineering (say: an HR rep for a tech company) are NOT &ldquo;Women In Tech.&rdquo; The conference was more about entrepreneurship than technical skills or the climate in the tech industry in Philadelphia. And the women who attended didn&rsquo;t seem like they knew anything about tech at all. One of the sponsors of the conference, TechGirlz, an organization that tries to encourage young girls to go into tech, is stating that tech is not all about knowing how to code. It really bothers me that an organization that should be promoting computer science is now undermining it as a way to attract a wider audience. Tech is definitely about coding and coding is fun!</p>

<p>Graduating in T-12 days: I have my cap and gown. On a daily basis, I get e-mails congratulating me on my achievement and telling me all the last-minute wrap-ups I need to do before Commencement. It seems surreal. I haven&rsquo;t actually started my job search yet. People keep telling me about opportunities and I&rsquo;m just not ready to apply yet. I&rsquo;m still finishing up CIS 555 - that&rsquo;s my main priority. Then I need a little rest because I&rsquo;ve been on edge with due dates pounding me every week for the past 2 years. I&rsquo;ll regain a little sanity and then begin applying to my future employer (whoever that may be).</p>

<p>I have nothing but wonderful things to say about the MCIT program and my professors who have helped me along the way. I am honored to have been chosen for the program and so happy to have successfully completed it. I&rsquo;m excited to see where my degree will take me!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reinventing the Wheel (or Web Server)]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/03/23/reinventing-the-wheel-or-web-server/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-23T09:10:53-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/03/23/reinventing-the-wheel-or-web-server</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My current (and final) course before I graduate has given me a new appreciation for Java packages. As developers, we use them all the time. In some cases, the more packages you know about, the more efficient and readable your code may be and the more sanity you get to keep.</p>

<p>My appreciation for packages has grown because the assignments I&rsquo;ve had to do for this course have basically asked me to build a number of things from scratch:</p>

<ul>
<li>A web server</li>
<li>An HTTP client</li>
<li>A thread pool</li>
<li>A servlet container</li>
<li>An XPath parser</li>
<li>An matcher between an XPath and an XML document.</li>
</ul>


<p>Of course, someone has already written the code to do all of these things in Java. It&rsquo;s either already built into Java or you can download a jar file to use it. But try writing these things from scratch and you&rsquo;ll find that you begin to write some of the nastiest code you&rsquo;ve ever written. Classes become horribly coupled, but that&rsquo;s the only way to make the application work. For writing your own servlet container, the API that describes the HttpRequest and HttpResponse interface methods is lacking. But it will make you appreciate Tomcat and all the work that went into making it.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s amusing that as a computer science student, I have been given a repetoire of principles to code by - DRY, KISS, YAGNI - and most of my assignments force me to violate them one way or another. Sure, writing certain functionality from scratch to really understand how things work under the covers is a great learning experience. But it&rsquo;s hardly simple when I could just import a package and use the classes/methods within it. Reinventing the wheel (or the web server, or the XPath parser, etc.) is a lot trickier than you&rsquo;d expect.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Year and a Half Later]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/01/28/a-year-and-a-half-later/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-28T16:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/01/28/a-year-and-a-half-later</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://LCBecker.github.io/images/comfortzone.jpg" alt="My favorite poster in Towne Building" /></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve started my last course before I graduate in May. Of course, in typical Lori-fashion, I decided to take one of the hardest courses the computer science department at UPenn has to offer: CIS 555 - Internet and Web Systems. Why did I want to take such a hard course? Why not just breeze my way through some easier class instead? Because this class is a true test of all I&rsquo;ve learned in the past year and a half. It will turn all of the things I&rsquo;ve studied and make me apply them in challenging, new ways.</p>

<p>The first assignment is to build a web server from scratch. I have to write EVERYTHING. I can&rsquo;t even use Java&rsquo;s concurrent library to implement a thread pool. I have to do everything myself. That&rsquo;s why I&rsquo;m writing this blog post. Procrastinating? No, not at all. The first step is always to think it through. Make a plan. Then execute. I&rsquo;m in the thinking phase, slowly making a plan.</p>

<p>Which is why I decided to write this blog post. I couldn&rsquo;t help but think about how crazy it is that I&rsquo;m actually taking this class and doing this assignment. A year and a half ago, I didn&rsquo;t know how to program. I didn&rsquo;t know what a &ldquo;data structure&rdquo; was. I didn&rsquo;t know what an &ldquo;algorithm&rdquo; was. I didn&rsquo;t know what a web server was. The internet was MAGIC. Software was MAGIC. Sometimes, I like to think about all the people on their cell phones, tablets, and computers for leisure or business and how they know NOTHING about the work that went into every detail of that device, the OS, and the software they&rsquo;re running. And I do. I do know (sort of) what it takes to make what most people take for granted as they use their gadgets. It&rsquo;s unbelievably impressive! More impressive: I can do these things!</p>

<p>This is really a testament to how great Penn&rsquo;s program is. The kid gloves were off before I stepped into my first class. I wanted to learn computer science and I was (as) ready (as I could be) for the challenge. I was worried, though. Could my professors really teach a photographer/English teacher how to write code? Yes, and they did. There were times when I felt like I was drowning, but I kept kicking. I went to sleep and found myself coding in my dreams (good code, too! Code I could use when I woke up!).</p>

<p>For anyone who thinks they don&rsquo;t fit the mold (mould for you UKers) for a particulary area of study, who thinks they&rsquo;re too old to learn something completely new &ndash; you can. It takes some getting used to when you&rsquo;re out of your comfort zone. But that&rsquo;s how you grow. That&rsquo;s how I got to where I am now.</p>

<p>What a difference a year and a half can make.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're Not Serious About Software Security]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/12/22/were-not-serious-about-software-security/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-22T11:22:10-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/12/22/were-not-serious-about-software-security</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Lulled Into A False Sense of Security</h3>

<p>It seems to happen every day and the public is appalled for about one second before it&rsquo;s back to business as usual. I&rsquo;m talking about hacking, not in the &ldquo;finding creative solutions&rdquo; sense, but the finding and exploiting of software vulnerabilities. Sony got hacked. Private e-mails and documents were released in retaliation for an &ldquo;unflattering&rdquo; movie about North Korea (supposedly). In past years, the big box stores have been hacked again and again. Customer credit card numbers were stolen. Still, people continue to swipe their credit cards at Target and Home Depot without blinking an eye.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re not serious about software security. The public doesn&rsquo;t care enough to change their habits and pressure companies to store their data safely and securely. And what can these companies do when they&rsquo;re at the mercy of the software company that developed the software they use?  Most software companies don&rsquo;t seem to care about exploits, unless it comes to their legal team, in which case, they&rsquo;ve already placed a disclaimer that using this software is at your own risk. So, these breaches seem to be par for the course. No one really takes responsibility. Another day, another hack.</p>

<h3>Universities: Software Security is a Choice, Not a Requirement</h3>

<p>This semester, I took a software engineering course which centered around the internal and external metrics of software quality as defined by ISO-9126. One of the external metrics was security. For software to be considered secure, it has to verify data is only accessible by authorized users and that code cannot be manipulated by outside sources. My professor showed us a few ways we could exploit programs in Java. Suddenly, everyone in the class realized how all the programs we&rsquo;d written throughout our careers as students (and possibly during our internships) were horribly insecure (Thanks, Java. Why SecurityManager is disabled by default, I&rsquo;ll never understand). And this was just in Java. What back doors exist in other programming languages?</p>

<p>Most university computer science programs have a computer and network security course. Unfortunately, it&rsquo;s usually an elective rather than a required course. Just do a Google search for &ldquo;required computer science courses&rdquo;. You&rsquo;ll see a list of university web sites, all of which list computer security as an elective course.</p>

<p>Digging further, what do students who take these computer security courses actually learn? Examining a wide variety of universities, the descriptions of these courses vary greatly. Some, like the <a href="http://www.colorado.edu/catalog/2013-14/courses/engr/b-csci/4133-security-laboratory">University of Colorado Boulder</a> give students hands-on experiences with finding and exploiting vulnerabilities. Right next door, <a href="http://www.cs.colostate.edu/~cs556/">Colorado State University&rsquo;s</a> computer security course states, &ldquo;In this course, we will begin by investigating some of the security measures that can be employed to safeguard information. For the most part we will look into the theory that goes into designing these measures rather than studying security tools and techniques. This is primarily because there are too many of those tools out there and they are changing frequently.&rdquo; Does a course that focuses more on theory than practice do a disservice to future software developers? Will Colorado State University&rsquo;s students create programs be as secure as say, the ones created by UC Boulder students who took Security Laboratory?</p>

<h3>Untraditional Routes: Learn To Code, Not Learn To Code Securely</h3>

<p>More and more people are taking different, untraditional routes into computer science. While it seems that teaching students how to write secure software is optional at the university level, these other paths into computer science seem to offer no instruction about writing secure software. Take, for example, the well-respected Flatiron School in New York. Nowhere in their <a href="http://prework.flatironschool.com/web-development/">curriculum</a> do they discuss security. The focus is on learning new technologies and writing code that works. Their graduates go off to work at well-known companies, just like university students, none-the-wiser about writing secure code.</p>

<p>Many other people are taking advantage of free online courses to teach themselves how to code. They could take this Coursera <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/softwaresec">course</a> on computer security, but the recommended background is for someone with a solid foundation in computer science, not someone trying to learn computer science on their own. I&rsquo;ll bet most self-learners won&rsquo;t be considering this course. The question is, will those already entrenched in computer science be motivated to take this course?</p>

<h3>Software Security is an Afterthought</h3>

<p>Without making software security a priority in our educational institutions and for hiring qualified software engineers, software will continue to be vulnerable to many preventable attacks. It&rsquo;s impossible to have an inpenetrable program. But there is so much we could do to make software more secure. If only there was some initiative on behalf of universities and other computer science-based schools to produce software developers who are knowledgeable in writing programs with some basic security measures in mind. And there needs to be more initiative on the part of companies to not only hire developers that are qualified to write working, secure code, but to take responsibility when their software leaks out sensitive information. As more and more of our lives become digitized, security should become a top priority, not an afterthought.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Type in Dvorak]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/11/13/why-i-type-in-dvorak/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-13T19:42:21-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/11/13/why-i-type-in-dvorak</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://LCBecker.github.io/images/dvorak.jpg" title="Dvorak keyboard" alt="Dvorak keyboard"></p>

<p>If you do a considerable amount of typing on a daily basis and have experienced stiffness or pain in the joints of your fingers, this post is for you. I used to have these problems, but a rather simple switch made all the difference.</p>

<h3>What is Dvorak?</h3>

<p>Dvorak is a keyboard layout in which the most commonly typed letters are on the home row. The layout was meant to increase typing speed and decrease typing fatigue. Dr. August Dvorak, a psychologist, and his brother-in-law, William Dealey, did extensive research on how people typed using the standard QWERTY keyboard. Dvorak thought QWERTY was inefficient and burdensome for users. In QWERTY, typing the most used letters requires users to move up or down from the home row and puts more emphasis on typing with the left hand. So, Dvorak and Dealey came up with the Dvorak Simplified Keyboard to tackle these inefficiencies.</p>

<h3>How Hard Was It To Learn?</h3>

<p>I typed in QWERTY for most of my life. I&rsquo;m sure many of you will remember being in elementary or middle school and taking a typing class where the teacher would call out letters and you&rsquo;d press the corresponding keys. Or maybe you played some typing game where you had to type &ldquo;garbage words&rdquo; as fast as you could and see if you could beat your best words per minute score.</p>

<p>Dvorak is not any different. You need to learn where the letters are and you need to practice. I found it easiest to buy some <a href="http://www.amazon.com/SIMPLIFIED-KEYBOARD-LETTERING-TRANSPARENT-BACKGROUND/dp/B0011FI3O8/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1416080332&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=dvorak+keyboard+stickers">Dvorak keyboard stickers</a> so I could look down at the keys to see where all the letters were until I could touch-type in Dvorak. I found a <a href="http://gigliwood.com/abcd/lessons/">nice website</a> to practice learning where the keys were and gain some speed. And I went cold-turkey and typed in Dvorak for work and home computer activities. In 2 weeks, I was typing 40 wpm and Dvorak seemed rather normal. After a year and a half of typing in Dvorak, I type about 80 wpm and I have exceptional accuracy &ndash; almost 99% according to the typing test I just took &ndash; and that&rsquo;s comparable or better to what I typed using QWERTY.</p>

<h3>Why Bother Learning Dvorak?</h3>

<p>The main benefit of learning Dvorak for me was to reduce finger joint pain. I once worked as a processing associate, a nice title for sitting in a cubicle all day and transcribing loads of documents into 3 different databases. I typed all day long, fingers glued to the keyboard. A year into that job, I had to go to an occupational therapist because I had extreme pain in my fingers to the point that I could not bend them at the joints. The therapist said my joints were swollen due to typing so much and that the best way to relieve the swelling was just not to type! Obviously, that wasn&rsquo;t an option.</p>

<p>I tried all sorts of &ldquo;ergonomic&rdquo; things to help alleviate pain caused by constant typing. I wore <a href="http://www.imakproducts.com/product.php?c=Wrist+/+Carpal+Tunnel&amp;s=10">wrist gloves</a> and had gel pads for the keyboard and mouse. I received a special keyboard at work with soft-press keys. But none of those things had any effect.</p>

<p>So, I learned Dvorak. Now, I type for at least 10 hours per day, every day, and I have not experienced the pain and stiffness in my fingers that I had as a processing associate. Dvorak was right: putting the important keys on the home row and dispersing what keys are pressed evenly between the left and right hand reduces finger/wrist strain. I&rsquo;ve never looked back on my decision to switch. It really helped me continue typing comfortably.</p>

<h3>What are Dvorak&rsquo;s Drawbacks?</h3>

<p>Well, for one, you&rsquo;ll selectively forget QWERTY. I can&rsquo;t touch-type in QWERTY anymore. Sit me at a computer with its keyboard set to QWERTY (which is the default keyboard layout, of course) and I&rsquo;m like a 5 year old pressing keys with my index finger when I find the key with the right letter on it. But I did say that forgetting QWERTY is <strong>selective</strong>. I can oddly type on a QWERTY keyboard no problem&ndash;wait for it&ndash;on my cell phone. Yes, that&rsquo;s right - the keyboard that pops up on my phone is in standard QWERTY and I have no issues swiping words or pressing individual letters. I oddly know where the letters reside even though I can&rsquo;t do this when sitting in front of an actual keyboard. I have no idea why this happens.</p>

<p>The second drawback is that there are other keyboard layouts out there that are specifically designed to alleviate repetitive strain injuries. They may be better than Dvorak. I&rsquo;ve never used them. Learning a second layout was enough for me…and it&rsquo;s one that is supported by most operating systems unlike some of these other layouts designed to help RSI.</p>

<p>The third drawback you might not even consider a drawback - other people can&rsquo;t type on your computer. So, if you do a lot of collaboration on your computer, you&rsquo;ll have to switch the keyboard back to QWERTY for those other users to type. But it is a lot of fun to hand someone your computer when the keyboard layout is set to Dvorak and see the havoc unfold as your colleague types in something and cannot understand why the computer spits out gibberish!</p>

<h3>Why I Love Dvorak</h3>

<p>The number one reason I love typing in Dvorak is, of course, that I am comfortable and pain-free. While there are some studies out there that dispute Dvorak&rsquo;s ability to alleviate RSI, it sure has for me. I enjoy knowing that someone can watch me type in my password, but they&rsquo;ll never know what it is just by watching what keys I press. I enjoy the fact that others cannot really use my computer because Dvorak keeps them from doing anything that cannot be accomplished without the keyboard. To sum it up, it&rsquo;s good for my health and my digital security. And it might be good for yours, too!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From Shakespeare to Java]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/10/08/from-shakespeare-to-java/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-08T21:56:58-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/10/08/from-shakespeare-to-java</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://LCBecker.github.io/images/engineeringbanner.jpg" title="Penn Engineering" alt="Penn Engineering"></p>

<p>A little more than a ago, I was a high school English teacher. I walked around a classroom supervising activities to help my students grasp key concepts of reading, writing, and the &ldquo;collective human experience.&rdquo; And yes, I did teach Shakespeare (&lsquo;Romeo and Juliet&rsquo; and &lsquo;Hamlet&rsquo; to be exact).</p>

<p><strong>So how does a high school English teacher become a software engineer?</strong></p>

<p>Three events happened simultaneously back in April 2013. The first was hitting my 5 year mark as a teacher and not having a permanent position. For 5 years, I had worked in 6 school districts, but the positions were always temporary. School districts were receiving less funding from the state, causing districts to remove teaching positions in favor of larger class sizes. Other districts were laying off teachers in the thousands, causing massive competition for any permanent position out there. I was frustrated. I was a great teacher, I loved my subject, and I loved the profession. But the opportunities were drying up more and more every day and my future was frighteningly uncertain.</p>

<p>The second event had been mulling around for a while, but became a beacon of hope in April. My best friend kept telling me I&rsquo;d make a fantastic software developer. He tried to convince me that computer science <em>is</em> a creative endeavor. He pointed out that I love puzzles (it&rsquo;s true - I do crosswords and logic puzzles on my smartphone all the time) and that writing code is like solving puzzles all day. The more he talked about it, the more interested I became. I considered teaching myself how to code using online resources or attending coding workshops, but then…</p>

<p>My best friend talked to one of his co-workers, who just happenend to have been an English major who went through the MCIT program at the University of Pennsylvania and received a Masters in computer science. It turned out the MCIT program was one of the few in the country that would take students from other disciplines and teach them all the fundamentals of computer science (and then some). After I heard about MCIT, I was pretty convinced that this was an opportunity of a lifetime. I didn&rsquo;t really know if I was going to like programming. But sometimes other people see more in us than we can see in ourselves. So, I applied to the MCIT program…and got accepted!</p>

<p>Today, I know my best friend was right…perhaps too right. Programming is a creative process. It is a long string of puzzles (&ldquo;How do I make the computer do <em>this</em>?&rdquo;). It is challenging, rewarding, frustrating, and awesome all at the same time.</p>

<p>My experience transitioning from English teacher to software engineer (or as I like to say, from Shakespeare to Java) is why I am such an advocate for teaching others about the field of computer science. I think that despite our leaps forward in technology and that most of us use computers and smartphones daily, we are extremely disconnected from what makes all of our electronics&#8217; functionality possible. The younger generation has to actively seek out what computer science is, because it is rarely taught in the public school system. I hope that in the future, more people are at least somewhat knowledgable about programming, even if it is at a very basic level.</p>

<p>So what does the future hold for an English teacher turned software engineer? I don&rsquo;t know, but I can&rsquo;t wait to find out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Trouble With Math in Computer Science Education]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/09/23/the-trouble-with-math-in-computer-science-education/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-23T21:04:27-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/09/23/the-trouble-with-math-in-computer-science-education</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://LCBecker.github.io/images/math.jpeg" title="math cartoon" alt="math cartoon"></p>

<p>Mathematics made computer science possible. From the Turing-Church papers to Von Neumann architecture, many of the things we take for granted are the direct result of some mathematician&rsquo;s discoveries.</p>

<p>University computer science programs require students to take math courses. To some extent, this is a reasonable requirement. Learning about DFAs and NFAs are the underpinning of creating compilers. Learning about relations is important in understanding database design. Clearly, mathematics has had a profound influence over computer science.</p>

<p>The irony is that only a small fraction of computer science graduates utilize the broad span of discrete mathematics and computational theory out in the workforce. So why are universities so set on requiring these courses to computer science students? Is it to <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2011/US/05/17/education.stem.graduation/">discourage</a> those &ldquo;on the fence&rdquo; about their area of study? Is it just that tradition is difficult to break? Or are these courses <em>truly</em> important (and if so, for who?)?</p>

<h3>The Mathematics Experience</h3>

<p>There are many reasons students struggle in the mathematics courses universities require for a degree in computer science. For one, American students generally come from schools that teach math in a rather ineffective way, as shown through numerous studies (the US Department of Education disputes this…imagine that). When students arrive in their Mathematical Foundations of Computer Science and Theory of Computation courses, they&rsquo;re ill prepared to handle the concepts being covered. This is especially true if they were not able to take higher level mathematics courses in high school.</p>

<p>In addition, as with most college courses, the material is taught in a &ldquo;one size fits all&rdquo; manner. The expectation is that students be responsible for their own learning, utilize recitations and office hours to ask questions, and find supplemental material to help them learn as needed. Unfortunately, a large portion of the mathematical concepts in computer science are so abstract that no matter what book, website, or video a student finds, the material is presented in <em>exactly</em> the same way as it was taught in class. If that method isn&rsquo;t helpful, there are no other recourses.</p>

<p>Finally, there&rsquo;s the problem of motivation. Students know they will not be writing proofs, drawing DFAs, or calculating the closure of a set of functional dependencies out in the workforce. For some students, these things may be exciting and worthwhile, but for others, learning these concepts is a waste of time. They take the course because it is a requirement, not because they are truly interested in the material or think it will be beneficial to their future career. And what happens when the course is over? ALL IS FORGOTTEN.</p>

<h3>The Push For Mathematical Theory in Computer Science</h3>

<p>Required mathematics courses may be lacking in practicality, but many computer science courses can also become bogged down in mathematical theory. Take, for instance, the topic of databases. Relational databases surely have their roots in relational algebra and calculus. To create a well-designed database, one must understand functional dependencies, closure, and algorithms for such things as BCNF. Yet, these concepts are mathematically intensive and for the average computer science student, they are completely unnecessary for learning how to work with the databases they will encounter after they graduate. The time invested in teaching mathematical theory takes away time to teach other, more practical skills and concepts in computer science.</p>

<h3>A Modest Proposal</h3>

<p>I propose that there should be two tracks of computer science. During a student&rsquo;s freshman year, they take courses that give a general overview of different areas of study within the field of computer science. This way, they are informed about the different careers available to them, from DBA to data scientist to front-end developer.</p>

<p>In the sophomore year, they begin to branch into one of two tracks. The first is more mathematically intensive and for good reason - their career paths require it. If a student wants to do machine learning, they need to have a good grasp of statistics, linear algebra, and calculus to write the code. It&rsquo;s really just that simple. There are certain areas of computer science that require a high level of mathematical prowess. This track is for students who wish to pursue those areas.</p>

<p>The other track is less concerned about mathematics. It still contains math coursework and in some cases, integrates mathematics into its computer science courses. The difference is that it teaches very practical math that is actually used to do specific tasks in computer science. Theoretical mathematics is left to the first track, since those students will benefit more from learning it. The students in this track may learn some of the same concepts as their peers in the first track, but in a more concrete way. For example, a student in this track may learn about relational databases and how lossless join works, but it will be taught using plain language, not in mathematical notation.</p>

<p>What about graduate school, you may be wondering. I still propose that there should be two options for certain courses, like Databases and Machine Learning. The University of Pennsylvania offered two machine learning courses at the graduate level this semester: one which was math intensive, one that was less so. Machine learning is so in demand by industry right now that it just makes sense to provide multiple ways of teaching the material to maximize the amount of people who understand and practice it. Clearly stripping away some of the mathematics in computer science courses can be done with great success and provide access to concepts that used to be reserved for the mathematically-inclined.</p>

<p>You may think I&rsquo;m advocating for dumbing down computer science by removing mathematics. I&rsquo;m not. What I am advocating for is making computer science coursework more tailored to the needs of both students and industry. It&rsquo;s time to reevaluate what is being taught in computer science courses and make room to teach what is truly important today and in the years to come.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
