<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[From Shakespeare to Java]]></title>
  <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-11T21:09:56-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lori Becker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/08/11/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-11T20:17:22-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/08/11/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One year ago, I didn&rsquo;t know what a while loop was nor a for loop nor an if-else statement. I thought inheritance was something I&rsquo;d get from my relatives. Classes were what I used to teach. You get the idea. One year ago, I was NOT a programmer.</p>

<p>A lot can happen in one year.</p>

<p>I was accepted into The University of Pennsylvania&rsquo;s Master of Computer and Information Technology program, designed for people with Bachelor&rsquo;s degrees in other areas of study. Considering the fact that I hold a B.S. in Photography and a M.A in Secondary English Education, this was the perfect program for me to learn the ins and outs of computer science.</p>

<p>At the end of my first semester, I was able to code in Scala, Java, and C (and assembly language, if you really want to be technical…which I&rsquo;m sure you do). I declared myself the GUI master after re-creating Frogger using Java Swing. I began adhering to test driven development, laughing as I found my stupid mistakes, cheering as code compiled with no errors, and Valgrind reported no memory leaks.</p>

<p>Flash forward to today. I am nearing the end of my summer internship as a Junior Developer. I&rsquo;ve completed one major project and one major component of a proof-of-concept project. Because of this, I felt compelled to begin writing about what I&rsquo;ve experienced and what I&rsquo;ve learned throughout this adventure into computer science.</p>

<p>Hello world indeed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
