<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ergonomics | From Shakespeare to Java]]></title>
  <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/categories/ergonomics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-05-25T09:09:10-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lori Becker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Kinesis FreeStyle2]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/02/24/the-kinesis-freestyle2/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-24T20:24:50-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/02/24/the-kinesis-freestyle2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/freestyle.jpg" title="&lsquo;kinesis keyboard&rsquo; &lsquo;kinesis keyboard&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>So, how&rsquo;s my new Kinesis FreeStyle2 keyboard? Is it as ergonomical as I need it to be relieve my RSI symptoms? Would it work well for you? Read on!</p>

<h3>Day 1</h3>

<p>I started my work day setting up the FreeStyle2 with the the VIP3 accessory kit. It took about 10 minutes, because I actually read directions :-P The wrist rests and the lifts snapped in nice and easy! I decided to use the largest angle, 15 degrees, for the lift. The more vertical it is, the more like that handshake position that&rsquo;s supposed to be ideal.</p>

<h4>Benefits of a Split Keyboard</h4>

<p>There are so many benefits of having a split keyboard. For one, my arms were so much more relaxed. Not only did it help my arms, but my back as well!</p>

<p>One surprising benefit of the split keyboard: the space in the middle! I was able to put my steno pad front and center! No longer was it off to the side so I&rsquo;d have to keep pivoting to look at my notes!</p>

<h4>Hotkey Blunder</h4>

<p>One of the things I was really looking forward having on the FreeStyle2 were the special keys on the left key panel. There are a variety of hotkeys including copy, paste, and select all. No more Command+C! So, as I was working, I found myself in situations that required copying and pasting text. Time to use the hotkeys! So, I highlighted some text, pressed the Copy hotkey&hellip;.and heard a &ldquo;ERRRR&rdquo; noise out of my headphones. I started pressing a variety of hotkeys and each one did not do as it was expected. One of the keys put Google Chrome in background mode (who knew Chome had such a thing as background mode?) and the others force quit some of my applications! YIKES!</p>

<p>I searched online, but no one reported issues with this keyboard&rsquo;s hotkeys. That could only mean one thing: Dvorak. I switched over to the Dvorak-Qwerty setting on my Mac and TA DA, the hotkeys worked!!!</p>

<h3>Week 1+</h3>

<p>Well, it&rsquo;s been one week of using my Kinesis keyboard. Some things have definitely changed since Day 1. Let&rsquo;s review:</p>

<h4>Goodbye, Hotkeys</h4>

<p>The hotkeys are still buggy. Really buggy. After switching to Dvorak-Qwerty, they worked, but only in certain applications. They didn&rsquo;t work in my main code editor, Eclipse. The applications where they did work made other Command+keys stopped working––one of which was the all important Command+S (Save). In my Atom editor, I apparently re-assigned keypresses by pressing Command+S. OOPS! Needless to say, I decided to go back to regular Dvorak, making the hotkeys useless again. At least I can actually save my work now.</p>

<h4>Tilt Good? Tilt Bad?</h4>

<p>I can&rsquo;t decide whether the 15 degree tilt is comfortable or not. I&rsquo;ve been experimenting now with the 10 degree tilt. I&rsquo;m not sure whether it&rsquo;s actually beneficial. The jury is still out on this one.</p>

<h4>Where Should My Mouse Go?</h4>

<p>I think this is the most fundamentally troubling question I&rsquo;ve been trying to answer this past week. The split keyboard makes my arms nice and comfortable, but only when <strong>typing</strong>. But my mouse is farther away, meaning I need to lean over to do all my clicking, moving of arrows, and scrolling. After a day or two of my new configuration, my right shoulder was really uncomfortable.</p>

<p>For a few days, I tried putting my mouse in the middle, between the two keyboard pads. But this is sadly also uncomfortable. It kind of negates the reason why I wanted a split keyboard in the first place&hellip;so my arms would not be at some unnatural angle in front of my body.</p>

<p>Lately, I&rsquo;ve tried doing as much as I can via the keyboard. I&rsquo;ve started learning the keypresses needed to toggle between tabs and applications. I&rsquo;ve used the page-down keys more for scrolling down on webpages. It&rsquo;s better than constantly reaching for the mouse. But the mouse is still essential and it&rsquo;s hard to know what else I can do to make using it more comfortable.</p>

<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m still very happy with my Kinesis FreeStyle2 purchase.</p>

<p><strong>PROS:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>It really has helped a lot with my wrist, arm, shoulder and finger pain.</li>
<li>That space in between the keypads is great for a notebook!</li>
<li>There&rsquo;s no learning curve to use it. It&rsquo;s a regular keyboard, just in a split configuration!</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>CONS:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Your mouse will be further away due to the split. There&rsquo;s probably no place to put your mouse in a comfortable position. You&rsquo;ll need to try learning more key shortcuts to do things you&rsquo;d normally do with your mouse so you don&rsquo;t need to reach for your mouse as much.</li>
<li>If you type in Dvorak, the hotkeys are useless.</li>
</ul>


<p>Thanks for reading!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Time for a New Keyboard]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/02/16/a-rant-about-ergonomics/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-16T17:10:38-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2016/02/16/a-rant-about-ergonomics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/kinesis.jpg" title="&lsquo;kinesis keyboard&rsquo; &lsquo;kinesis keyboard&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about ergonomics lately. A few weeks ago, I thought I was dreaming as I looked down and saw that my little finger&rsquo;s bone had somehow managed to overlap my ring finger&rsquo;s bone. My hand looked like a claw! I had to use my other hand to set my finger bones back in shape.</p>

<p>I knew I had to do something. I love software engineering, but let&rsquo;s face it––it&rsquo;s sort of a crippling job. Sitting all day: Not good. Typing/mousing all day: Not good.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve written <a href="http://lcbecker.github.io/blog/2014/11/13/why-i-type-in-dvorak/">before</a> about how switching to Dvorak helped alleviate my RSI. But clearly, it was back. A simple search discovered that the Apple Magic Bluetooth keyboard is absolutely AWFUL for RSI. Time for a new keyboard&hellip;</p>

<h3>Ye Old Keyboard</h3>

<p>First, I brought my old Logitech keyboard to work. This poor keyboard has been sitting collecting dust in front of my desktop (which was last turned on&hellip;hmm&hellip;3 years ago?). Right away, there was a problem––the number pad on the right. I felt like my mouse was so far away and my right arm was forced to be at a 60 degree angle from my body to type. Awkward!</p>

<h3>The Kinesis Classic QD</h3>

<p>Thankfully, a friend allowed me to borrow his Kinesis Classic QD keyboard (pictured above) to get a feel for it. He swears by it after suffering himself from RSI and has been using it for years! This is probably one of the strangest keyboards I&rsquo;ve ever seen, but it has a lot going for it. The wrist pads are perfectly positioned. The inset wells for the keys puts your fingers at a natural downward tilt. And what I loved most of all––the division between left and right puts your arms perpendicular to your body, which is way more comfortable than having them angled to the middle of your body! It also has the keys you probably press the most pushed to the thumb regions. The keys can be remapped in whatever configuration you prefer.</p>

<p>After trying the Kinesis Classic (newer versions are called the <a href="https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/shop/advantage-for-pc-mac/">Advantage</a>) for a week, it was clear what I loved and hated about this keyboard. And what I hated was the key configurations. I have tiny hands, so using any of the thumb buttons was actually putting a lot of strain on my wrists to twist and reach those buttons. Even though I could remap keys, it was really difficult getting used to pressing keys that I was used to being placed in areas of the keyboard that no longer existed in the Kinesis key layout. Yet, this trial run was enough to convince me that Kinesis was on to something&hellip;</p>

<h3>The Kinesis FreeStyle2</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ll write a post about my experiences with this keyboard once I get it later this week. However, I think the Kinesis <a href="https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/shop/freestyle2-for-mac/">FreeStyle2</a> has everything I loved about the Classic without all the things I disliked. I bought the 20&#8221; extension for that great left/right arm separation. I also purchased the optional VIP3 accessory package that allows you to vertically tilt the keyboard. Supposedly, the &ldquo;handshake&rdquo; position is better for your wrists and arms. If you have pain in your lower arm, this might be great for you. The VIP3 also comes with Kinesis&#8217; awesome wrist pads (seriously, they&rsquo;re worth raving about!).</p>

<p><em>Stay Tuned For More On My Journey into Being More Ergonomical!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
