<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Jersey | From Shakespeare to Java]]></title>
  <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/categories/jersey/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-10-24T21:32:26-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lori Becker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HTTPS With Jersey]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/10/26/https-with-jersey/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-26T20:16:51-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/10/26/https-with-jersey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am so excited about this post! It&rsquo;s a technical post! With code! I wanted to write this to help others who might find themselves in the same predicament.</p>

<p>This was the issue: I&rsquo;m writing a DropWizard application. DropWizard uses Jersey. My application needed to take in a POST request and use the post body to make a POST request to a trusted server using HTTPS. But then this error showed up:</p>

<pre><code>ERROR [2015-10-22 20:41:23,405] io.dropwizard.jersey.errors.LoggingExceptionMapper: Error handling a request: 8d10b79e51bbb14d
! java.lang.IllegalStateException: AlreadyConnected
! at sun.net.www.protocol.http.HttpsUrlConnection.setRequestProperty(Unknown Source)...
</code></pre>

<p>After doing a little Googling, I found out that the exception is mislabeled. Jersey shouldn&rsquo;t be throwing an IllegalStateException. It should be a SSLHandshakeException. Ok, so the question is: What&rsquo;s the workaround? We need to get Jersey (version 2) to accept a self-signed SSL certificate. This requires creating a class with a method we can call to help build a client with the needed configurations. I created this class exactly as Aleksandr Panzin demonstrated <a href="https://gist.github.com/JAlexoid/b15dba31e5919586ae51">here</a>.</p>

<p>Once I added the <code>JerseyWithSSL</code> class, I realized, &ldquo;Hey, Aleksandr didn&rsquo;t explain how to actually use it!&rdquo; And so now, I provide to you the complete solution! Back in my resources class, I created a client using the <code>JerseyWithSSL</code> method <code>initClient()</code>:</p>

<pre><code>import java.security.KeyManagementException;
import java.security.NoSuchAlgorithmException;
import javax.ws.rs.POST;
import javax.ws.rs.client.Client;
import org.glassfish.jersey.client.ClientConfig;

@Path("/ticket")
public class Ticket

@POST
public Response createTicket(...) {
    ClientConfig cc = new ClientConfig();
    Client client = null;
    try {
        client = new JerseyWithSSL().initClient(cc);
    } catch (KeyManagementException e) {
        e.printStackTrace();
    } catch (NoSuchAlgorithmException e) { 
        e.printStackTrace();
    }

// Use client as you need...
</code></pre>

<p>The trick was figuring out what exactly the <code>Configuration</code> parameter was supposed to be in the <code>initClient()</code> method. An instance of <code>ClientConfig</code> did the trick. I&rsquo;m happy to say my application works due to this code! Hopefully, it will help you if you ever come across this error.</p>

<p>Happy Coding!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
