<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Education | From Shakespeare to Java]]></title>
  <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/categories/education/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-29T18:22:20-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lori Becker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From Shakespeare to Java]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/10/08/from-shakespeare-to-java/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-08T21:56:58-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/10/08/from-shakespeare-to-java</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/engineeringbanner.jpg" title="&lsquo;Penn Engineering&rsquo; &lsquo;Penn Engineering&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>A little more than a ago, I was a high school English teacher. I walked around a classroom supervising activities to help my students grasp key concepts of reading, writing, and the &ldquo;collective human experience.&rdquo; And yes, I did teach Shakespeare (&lsquo;Romeo and Juliet&rsquo; and &lsquo;Hamlet&rsquo; to be exact).</p>

<p><strong>So how does a high school English teacher become a software engineer?</strong></p>

<p>Three events happened simultaneously back in April 2013. The first was hitting my 5 year mark as a teacher and not having a permanent position. For 5 years, I had worked in 6 school districts, but the positions were always temporary. School districts were receiving less funding from the state, causing districts to remove teaching positions in favor of larger class sizes. Other districts were laying off teachers in the thousands, causing massive competition for any permanent position out there. I was frustrated. I was a great teacher, I loved my subject, and I loved the profession. But the opportunities were drying up more and more every day and my future was frighteningly uncertain.</p>

<p>The second event had been mulling around for a while, but became a beacon of hope in April. My best friend kept telling me I&rsquo;d make a fantastic software developer. He tried to convince me that computer science <em>is</em> a creative endeavor. He pointed out that I love puzzles (it&rsquo;s true - I do crosswords and logic puzzles on my smartphone all the time) and that writing code is like solving puzzles all day. The more he talked about it, the more interested I became. I considered teaching myself how to code using online resources or attending coding workshops, but then…</p>

<p>My best friend talked to one of his co-workers, who just happenend to have been an English major who went through the MCIT program at the University of Pennsylvania and received a Masters in computer science. It turned out the MCIT program was one of the few in the country that would take students from other disciplines and teach them all the fundamentals of computer science (and then some). After I heard about MCIT, I was pretty convinced that this was an opportunity of a lifetime. I didn&rsquo;t really know if I was going to like programming. But sometimes other people see more in us than we can see in ourselves. So, I applied to the MCIT program…and got accepted!</p>

<p>Today, I know my best friend was right…perhaps too right. Programming is a creative process. It is a long string of puzzles (&ldquo;How do I make the computer do <em>this</em>?&rdquo;). It is challenging, rewarding, frustrating, and awesome all at the same time.</p>

<p>My experience transitioning from English teacher to software engineer (or as I like to say, from Shakespeare to Java) is why I am such an advocate for teaching others about the field of computer science. I think that despite our leaps forward in technology and that most of us use computers and smartphones daily, we are extremely disconnected from what makes all of our electronics&#8217; functionality possible. The younger generation has to actively seek out what computer science is, because it is rarely taught in the public school system. I hope that in the future, more people are at least somewhat knowledgable about programming, even if it is at a very basic level.</p>

<p>So what does the future hold for an English teacher turned software engineer? I don&rsquo;t know, but I can&rsquo;t wait to find out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Trouble With Math in Computer Science Education]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/09/23/the-trouble-with-math-in-computer-science-education/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-23T21:04:27-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/09/23/the-trouble-with-math-in-computer-science-education</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/math.jpeg" title="&lsquo;math cartoon&rsquo; &lsquo;math cartoon&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Mathematics made computer science possible. From the Turing-Church papers to Von Neumann architecture, many of the things we take for granted are the direct result of some mathematician&rsquo;s discoveries.</p>

<p>University computer science programs require students to take math courses. To some extent, this is a reasonable requirement. Learning about DFAs and NFAs are the underpinning of creating compilers. Learning about relations is important in understanding database design. Clearly, mathematics has had a profound influence over computer science.</p>

<p>The irony is that only a small fraction of computer science graduates utilize the broad span of discrete mathematics and computational theory out in the workforce. So why are universities so set on requiring these courses to computer science students? Is it to <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2011/US/05/17/education.stem.graduation/">discourage</a> those &ldquo;on the fence&rdquo; about their area of study? Is it just that tradition is difficult to break? Or are these courses <em>truly</em> important (and if so, for who?)?</p>

<h3>The Mathematics Experience</h3>

<p>There are many reasons students struggle in the mathematics courses universities require for a degree in computer science. For one, American students generally come from schools that teach math in a rather ineffective way, as shown through numerous studies (the US Department of Education disputes this…imagine that). When students arrive in their Mathematical Foundations of Computer Science and Theory of Computation courses, they&rsquo;re ill prepared to handle the concepts being covered. This is especially true if they were not able to take higher level mathematics courses in high school.</p>

<p>In addition, as with most college courses, the material is taught in a &ldquo;one size fits all&rdquo; manner. The expectation is that students be responsible for their own learning, utilize recitations and office hours to ask questions, and find supplemental material to help them learn as needed. Unfortunately, a large portion of the mathematical concepts in computer science are so abstract that no matter what book, website, or video a student finds, the material is presented in <em>exactly</em> the same way as it was taught in class. If that method isn&rsquo;t helpful, there are no other recourses.</p>

<p>Finally, there&rsquo;s the problem of motivation. Students know they will not be writing proofs, drawing DFAs, or calculating the closure of a set of functional dependencies out in the workforce. For some students, these things may be exciting and worthwhile, but for others, learning these concepts is a waste of time. They take the course because it is a requirement, not because they are truly interested in the material or think it will be beneficial to their future career. And what happens when the course is over? ALL IS FORGOTTEN.</p>

<h3>The Push For Mathematical Theory in Computer Science</h3>

<p>Required mathematics courses may be lacking in practicality, but many computer science courses can also become bogged down in mathematical theory. Take, for instance, the topic of databases. Relational databases surely have their roots in relational algebra and calculus. To create a well-designed database, one must understand functional dependencies, closure, and algorithms for such things as BCNF. Yet, these concepts are mathematically intensive and for the average computer science student, they are completely unnecessary for learning how to work with the databases they will encounter after they graduate. The time invested in teaching mathematical theory takes away time to teach other, more practical skills and concepts in computer science.</p>

<h3>A Modest Proposal</h3>

<p>I propose that there should be two tracks of computer science. During a student&rsquo;s freshman year, they take courses that give a general overview of different areas of study within the field of computer science. This way, they are informed about the different careers available to them, from DBA to data scientist to front-end developer.</p>

<p>In the sophomore year, they begin to branch into one of two tracks. The first is more mathematically intensive and for good reason - their career paths require it. If a student wants to do machine learning, they need to have a good grasp of statistics, linear algebra, and calculus to write the code. It&rsquo;s really just that simple. There are certain areas of computer science that require a high level of mathematical prowess. This track is for students who wish to pursue those areas.</p>

<p>The other track is less concerned about mathematics. It still contains math coursework and in some cases, integrates mathematics into its computer science courses. The difference is that it teaches very practical math that is actually used to do specific tasks in computer science. Theoretical mathematics is left to the first track, since those students will benefit more from learning it. The students in this track may learn some of the same concepts as their peers in the first track, but in a more concrete way. For example, a student in this track may learn about relational databases and how lossless join works, but it will be taught using plain language, not in mathematical notation.</p>

<p>What about graduate school, you may be wondering. I still propose that there should be two options for certain courses, like Databases and Machine Learning. The University of Pennsylvania offered two machine learning courses at the graduate level this semester: one which was math intensive, one that was less so. Machine learning is so in demand by industry right now that it just makes sense to provide multiple ways of teaching the material to maximize the amount of people who understand and practice it. Clearly stripping away some of the mathematics in computer science courses can be done with great success and provide access to concepts that used to be reserved for the mathematically-inclined.</p>

<p>You may think I&rsquo;m advocating for dumbing down computer science by removing mathematics. I&rsquo;m not. What I am advocating for is making computer science coursework more tailored to the needs of both students and industry. It&rsquo;s time to reevaluate what is being taught in computer science courses and make room to teach what is truly important today and in the years to come.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learn to Code: Let Me Count the Ways]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/09/04/learn-to-code-let-me-count-the-ways/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-04T20:40:12-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2014/09/04/learn-to-code-let-me-count-the-ways</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/codeevolution.jpg" title="&lsquo;evolution&rsquo; &lsquo;evolution&rsquo;" ></p>

<h6>The Evolution of Computer Programming Languages by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/dullhunk/4833512699/">dullhunk</a></h6>

<p>Learning to code has become a heated topic these days. I read <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/technology-topics/11064505/Creating-a-British-Mark-Zuckerberg-is-all-about-Education-Education-Education.html">this</a> critical article about the UK&rsquo;s decision to teach children to code as part of the curriculum. Then there was <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/future_tense/2014/09/01/labor_day_2014_tech_skills_are_important_in_the_workplace_but_so_are_other.html">this</a> article about how tech skills are overvalued in today&rsquo;s marketplace. And not to be outdone, there was <a href="http://www.theepochtimes.com/n3/927675-computer-science-majors-your-degree-may-not-be-as-valuable-as-you-think/">this</a> about how even if a person does get a degree in computer science, they might not have the skills companies want.</p>

<p>So, is learning to code important? If so, should it be a manditory class in elementary/secondary education? If someone wants to learn to code, should they teach themselves for free using the many sites online? What about attending a coding bootcamp? Does majoring in computer science at a college/university really give someone an edge when looking for a software engineering position?</p>

<h3>Is Coding Important?</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s first define &ldquo;important.&rdquo; My definition of important is: useful, bordering on necessary to function in some capacity. In the developed world, I&rsquo;m pretty sure most people would say coding is important. Think of all the things that depend on code for their functionality. Without code, there would be no cell phones and all those apps we love so much. There would be no jobs that use a computer. In our cars, the fancy touchscreens that tell us the traffic on our way to and from work&mdash;gone. The microwave, oven, dishwasher, and wifi connected television would be pretty much useless. The list goes on and on. People who knew how to code made these things possible. It&rsquo;s important that many people know how to code since so much of the convenience of our daily lives depends on it.</p>

<h3>Teaching Children To Code</h3>

<p>The controversy about teaching programming in schools is really a controversy about a broader issue. Is what we teach children in school <em>relevant</em> in today&rsquo;s modern world? Since coding is important in our technology-driven society, it seems <em>relevent</em> to teach it to children. But how many children, and when? Not every child is going to become a software engineer, so some would argue a computer science course should not be a mandatory part of the curriculum. Yet certain other courses are mandatory, like physical education and foreign languages, but children aren&rsquo;t expected to become professional athletes or translators. Those types of courses teach children about healthy lifestyles and other cultures accordingly. Students must take them so they are &ldquo;well-rounded.&rdquo;</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d argue computer science fits into that &ldquo;well-rounded&rdquo; objective. I was never exposed to computer science in school, so it was never on my radar to learn it. However, I was exposed to art, music, keyboard typing, woodworking, sewing, home economics, Spanish, German, and French in my middle school years (6 - 8). Why not add computer science to the list of &ldquo;exposure courses.&rdquo; Students should be exposed to writing code so they know what it&rsquo;s like and what it can do. If students enjoy learning to program, they can take it as an elective in high school or even pursue it in college. Most schools around the world teach history, so students understand how the world they live in came to be. Computer science will also teach them how the world they live in came to be.</p>

<h3>Learning to Code Through Online Tutorials</h3>

<p>The number of websites that teach visitors to code is <em>staggering</em>. There&rsquo;s <a href="http://http://www.codecademy.com/">Codecademy</a>, <a href="http://www.codeschool.com">Code School</a>, and <a href="http://learn.code.org/">Code.org</a> to name a few. There are also free online courses through sites like <a href="https://www.udacity.com/">Udacity</a> and MIT&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.edx.org/">EdX</a> that people can take to learn to code.</p>

<p>Before I started the MCIT program, I thought I&rsquo;d give myself a heads-up before classes began and take the Python course on Codecademy. I went through each cutesy little exercise, but truth be told, I didn&rsquo;t know what I was doing. Nothing really sunk in. I followed the directions, made guesses on the open-ended exercises, but I didn&rsquo;t see the big picture about what I could really do with if statements and while loops. Making a tip calculator was nice, but too simplistic a view of what coding can <em>really</em> do. That&rsquo;s my opinion. Maybe there are others for whom Codecademy opened doors to all the possibilities! It wasn&rsquo;t for me (when I was a beginner). Note: If you already know how to code and want to learn a new programming language or framework, these websites are invaluable!</p>

<p>I believe in a more structured approach to teaching computer science. For the budget-conscious or for those who want to learn to code to move up in their career, taking courses through Udacity or EdX might be the way to go. It requires the user to be motivated, to put in the time to learn (much more time than it will take going through a Codecademy course), and to be ready for some difficult challenges. These courses are more thorough and will make students better prepared should they want to dive deeper into computer science.</p>

<h3>Learning to Code By Going to a Bootcamp</h3>

<p>Coding bootcamps have started cropping up everywhere in the past few years. Click <a href="http://bootcamper.io/t/type/in-class">here</a> to see an exhaustive list of them! Many of these bootcamps are specialized schools, focusing on one programming language or skill. They&rsquo;re quicker than a college education and cheaper than one, too, but students only learn &ldquo;skills employers want.&rdquo; Some of these schools are partnered with companies that will hire graduates of the program - that&rsquo;s great! But are the students coming out of these schools really prepared to work in the tech industry? Do they know about best practices like what data structure to use in certain situations? Do they practice any test driven development? Will they be relevant in later years when iOS has been replaced by a better mobile OS? What if Ruby becomes obsolete? Will the students of these bootcamps be able to adapt?</p>

<p>These bootcamps seem better for meeting short-term goals and for people who need structure to motivate them. So they may be a step up from online courses at Udacity and EdX, but their long-term success remains to be seen.</p>

<h3>Learning To Code By Studying Computer Science</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s interesting how college computer science courses have come under fire for not providing graduates the skills employers want. Employers want people with a broad assortment of technical know-how. It&rsquo;s not just programming languages, but frameworks, databases, specific operating systems, version control systems, testing applications…the list goes on and on! Do colleges teach these skills or are they really more &ldquo;theory driven?&rdquo;</p>

<p>I can only speak about my experience studying computer science at the graduate level. The courses I&rsquo;ve taken taught me four programming languages, a tad about version control using Git, and test driven development using JUnit for Java. I&rsquo;ve also had courses that taught a lot of theory. I balked at having to take a Discrete Mathematics course. I&rsquo;ll never be writing induction proofs ever again! Yet, the topic of relations came up in my databases course this week and I knew what that really meant because I learned all about it in Discrete Mathematics. Does it really matter that I understand how a relational database works? Maybe not, but it might come in handy somewhere down the line. I didn&rsquo;t think knowing relations was important, but databases today wouldn&rsquo;t be the same without it!</p>

<p>Theory is dismissed as fluff by critics, but they do not seem to understand that theory is what makes <em>reality</em>. People who learn theory can then apply it to real-world situations. Computational theory influenced Alan Turing who, in turn, theorized the Turing machine (which you can now make out of <a href="http://youtu.be/cYw2ewoO6c4">Legos</a>…), and was the basis of all computing today. Brilliant people know both theory and current, practical skills. They can adapt because they see The Big Picture.</p>

<p>Employers may want people with skills, but they also want people with experience. Knowing this fact will help you choose a good college with a good program. Colleges cannot teach students everything for the workplace, because employers vary widely in what they do! That&rsquo;s why it&rsquo;s important to choose a university that balances theory with practical applications and provides internship opportunities to gain experience in the field.</p>

<p>For these reasons, employers may value someone with a college degree in computer science more highly than someone with the same skillset without a degree. Someone who really understands the ins-and-outs of computer science might be able to adapt to changes in technology more easily than someone who has been self-taught. But employers keep their options open. There are many programmers out there without a college education who are doing great work. It&rsquo;s clearly not the end of the world to know how to code and not have a college degree in computer science. However, it may be more difficult to find a programming position considering many large companies require their developers to have a computer science degree.</p>

<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>

<p>Learning to code is important, if only to understand how modern technology works. If you&rsquo;re interested in coding, there are tons of online resources, workshops, bootcamps, and colleges ready to help you on your way. Choose what&rsquo;s best for your style of learning and level of motivation. There is no one right way to learn how to code. There&rsquo;s only <em>your</em> way.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
