<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Java | From Shakespeare to Java]]></title>
  <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/categories/java/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-29T18:22:20-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lori Becker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DropWizard Metrics 101]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/11/18/dropwizard-metrics-101/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-18T18:18:54-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/11/18/dropwizard-metrics-101</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/metrics.jpg" title="&lsquo;metrics art&rsquo; &lsquo;metrics art&rsquo;" ></p>

<h6>IO Graph Art by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/nathanmac87/4415951740">nathanmac87</a></h6>

<p><strong>Post revised 11/23/2015 for correctness. Thank you to Jan-Olav Eide and Tim Bart for leading me in the right direction!</strong></p>

<p>My most recent project at work has been to utilize DropWizard metrics to gather information about an application I built and send that data to Graphite to display in a realtime dashboard. As I normally do, I reviewed the documentation for <a href="https://dropwizard.github.io/metrics/3.1.0/getting-started/">Dropwizard Metrics</a>, but as usual, there was a lot to be desired. Their example did not go into the nitty gritty of <em>how</em> to connect everything together. The internet was also silent on how to actually use DropWizard metrics.</p>

<p>So here is my tutorial on how <em>I</em> was able to get DropWizard metrics up and running in my application:</p>

<h3>1. Maven Application? Update pom.xml</h3>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve got a Maven application, you&rsquo;ll need to add metrics-core as a dependency. If you&rsquo;re using some sort of special reporter like Graphite, you may need to add additional dependencies. This was what I had to add to my pom:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;io.dropwizard.metrics&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;metrics-core&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;3.1.0&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;
&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;io.dropwizard.metrics&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;metrics-graphite&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;3.1.0&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;
&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;io.dropwizard&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;dropwizard-metrics-graphite&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;0.9.1&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;
</code></pre>

<h3>2. Start Your Metrics On Application Startup</h3>

<p>Supposedly, there are two ways you can initialize your metrics reporters. A reporter sends your data to either the console, logger, Graphite, or other DropWizard-approved outputs. You can either specify them in your config.yml file, as seen <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/29432586/dropwizard-yaml-for-graphite-server-configuration">here</a>. This is supposed to start reporting your metrics automatically when you start your application. I tried this method, but I had zero luck with it. I ended up getting some parsing error from within DropWizard&rsquo;s validation library.</p>

<p>So, I initialized my metrics an alternative way&ndash; in the <code>run()</code> method of my application class. DropWizard&rsquo;s environment already creates a <code>MetricRegistry</code> object on startup. This object manages all of our metrics (these are timers, counters, meters, histograms, and gauges). Since I added metrics to my resources class, I needed to pass that <code>MetricRegistry</code> object to my resource class. This is how my application class looked:</p>

<pre><code>public class MyApplication extends Application&lt;MyConfiguration&gt;{

    public static void main(String[] args) throws Exception {
        new MyApplication().run(args);
    }

    @Override
    public void run(MyConfiguration config, Environment env) throws Exception {

        final Graphite graphite = new Graphite(new InetSocketAddress("my.graphite.host", 2003));

        final GraphiteReporter reporter = GraphiteReporter.forRegistry(env.metrics())
            .prefixedWith("upToYou")
            .convertRatesTo(TimeUnit.SECONDS)
            .convertDurationsTo(TimeUnit.MILLISECONDS)
            .filter(MetricFilter.ALL)
            .build(graphite);
        reporter.start(5, TimeUnit.SECONDS);
        environment.jersey().register(new MyResource(env.metrics()));
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Some things to note: The <code>prefixedWith</code> is not required. What this does is append a label in front of our metrics names. I&rsquo;ll explain this more in Step 3.</p>

<h3>3. Add Metrics To Your Resources</h3>

<p>I wanted metrics like &lsquo;How many requests are we getting at /path1&rsquo; and &lsquo;How long is it taking for the method handling /path1 to return a response&rsquo;. Chances are you are, too. In order to do this, we&rsquo;ll need to add metrics to our resources. And those metrics need to be &ldquo;saved&rdquo; in the <code>MetricRegistry</code> from Step 2. So we&rsquo;ll need to create a constructor for our resource that will take in the <code>MetricRegistry</code> object we passed in Step 2.</p>

<p>There are two ways to add metrics to your resources: using annotations and by actually creating objects of a metrics class. I&rsquo;ll give you an example of both:</p>

<pre><code>public class MyResource {
     MetricRegistry metrics;
     Meter requestCount;

     public MyResource(MetricRegistry registry) {
        this.metrics = registry;
        requestCount = metrics.meter(MetricRegister.name("requestCount"));
     }

     @POST
     @Path("/path1")
     @Produces(MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN)
     @Timed(absolute=true, name="requestRuntime")
     public Response handleRequest() {
        requestCount.mark();
        return Response.ok("Hello World").build(); //you know what I mean...
     }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Notice these details:</p>

<ul>
<li>We declare the meter <code>requestCount</code>, which will give us the total count of all calls made to /path1 and how many requests /path1 gets in 1 minute, 5 minute, and 15 minute timeframes. We initialized this <code>Meter</code> object in our Resource constructor, It&rsquo;s initialization uses our <code>MetricRegistry</code> so it can manage it accordingly.</li>
<li>See the <code>@Timed</code> annotation? DropWizard will automatically create a timer and whenever <code>handleRequest()</code> is called, the timer will record how long it takes to complete this method. We do not need to initialize a timer object ourselves. We can name this timer. I&rsquo;ve added the <code>absolute=true</code> field, because otherwise, the entire path of this metric in Graphite will be my prefix + package path + class + requestRuntime. Too long! By setting absolute to true, the metric path is just the prefix + the metric name.</li>
<li>Remember in Step 2 when we saw that <code>.prefixedWith("upToYou")</code>? Basically, our reporter, whether Graphite or the console or something else, will refer to this metric by the prefix + name of the metric. Graphite showed me options to graph like, &ldquo;upToYou.requestCount.count&rdquo; and &ldquo;upToYou.requestCount.mean&rdquo; (the &lsquo;count&rsquo; and &lsquo;mean&rsquo; part are automatically attached by DropWizard metrics). You don&rsquo;t need any prefix, but if you want it, go for it back in Step 2.</li>
<li>Finally, we call our meter&rsquo;s <code>mark()</code> method. That tells the metric, &ldquo;Hey, the method we&rsquo;re tracking has been called! Increment the meter count!&rdquo; The <code>mark()</code> method is for the meter metric, though. Please refer to the <a href="https://dropwizard.github.io/metrics/3.1.0/getting-started/">DropWizard Metrics</a> documentation on how to initialize and call counters, histograms, and other metrics. Now, here we&rsquo;ve programmatically called the meter&rsquo;s method. We don&rsquo;t have to do that. We could just use the annotation <code>@Metered(absolute=true, name="myMeter")</code> and DropWizard would automatically call <code>mark()</code> for us whenever our method was called. But this is how you would do it if you wanted additional control&hellip;or multiple meters on a single method.</li>
</ul>


<h3>4. Profit</h3>

<p>Now, when we start up our application, our metrics will be monitoring what we want and sending data to the console or Graphite or wherever!</p>

<p>So, there you have it! This is how everything ties together in DropWizard Metrics! And I&rsquo;m the first person to actually write an example of this! Woohoo! I hope you have enjoyed this post and that it&rsquo;s given you a decent amount of confidence to use DropWizard metrics in your application! Happy Coding!</p>

<p>If you really like this, tell me on Twitter @LBeckerCodes !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HTTPS With Jersey]]></title>
    <link href="http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/10/26/https-with-jersey/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-26T20:16:51-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://LCBecker.github.io/blog/2015/10/26/https-with-jersey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am so excited about this post! It&rsquo;s a technical post! With code! I wanted to write this to help others who might find themselves in the same predicament.</p>

<p>This was the issue: I&rsquo;m writing a DropWizard application. DropWizard uses Jersey. My application needed to take in a POST request and use the post body to make a POST request to a trusted server using HTTPS. But then this error showed up:</p>

<pre><code>ERROR [2015-10-22 20:41:23,405] io.dropwizard.jersey.errors.LoggingExceptionMapper: Error handling a request: 8d10b79e51bbb14d
! java.lang.IllegalStateException: AlreadyConnected
! at sun.net.www.protocol.http.HttpsUrlConnection.setRequestProperty(Unknown Source)...
</code></pre>

<p>After doing a little Googling, I found out that the exception is mislabeled. Jersey shouldn&rsquo;t be throwing an IllegalStateException. It should be a SSLHandshakeException. Ok, so the question is: What&rsquo;s the workaround? We need to get Jersey (version 2) to accept a self-signed SSL certificate. This requires creating a class with a method we can call to help build a client with the needed configurations. I created this class exactly as Aleksandr Panzin demonstrated <a href="https://gist.github.com/JAlexoid/b15dba31e5919586ae51">here</a>.</p>

<p>Once I added the <code>JerseyWithSSL</code> class, I realized, &ldquo;Hey, Aleksandr didn&rsquo;t explain how to actually use it!&rdquo; And so now, I provide to you the complete solution! Back in my resources class, I created a client using the <code>JerseyWithSSL</code> method <code>initClient()</code>:</p>

<pre><code>import java.security.KeyManagementException;
import java.security.NoSuchAlgorithmException;
import javax.ws.rs.POST;
import javax.ws.rs.client.Client;
import org.glassfish.jersey.client.ClientConfig;

@Path("/ticket")
public class Ticket

@POST
public Response createTicket(...) {
    ClientConfig cc = new ClientConfig();
    Client client = null;
    try {
        client = new JerseyWithSSL().initClient(cc);
    } catch (KeyManagementException e) {
        e.printStackTrace();
    } catch (NoSuchAlgorithmException e) { 
        e.printStackTrace();
    }

// Use client as you need...
</code></pre>

<p>The trick was figuring out what exactly the <code>Configuration</code> parameter was supposed to be in the <code>initClient()</code> method. An instance of <code>ClientConfig</code> did the trick. I&rsquo;m happy to say my application works due to this code! Hopefully, it will help you if you ever come across this error.</p>

<p>Happy Coding!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
